<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Java | Mike Murray]]></title>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/categories/java/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-03T19:32:09-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mkmurray.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Murray]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Variable Declaration Restrictions]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/09/23/variable-declaration-restrictions/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-23T16:09:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/09/23/variable-declaration-restrictions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I came across a surprising restriction on variable declarations that I thought I would share.</p>  <p>My own investigation into C# was prompted by <a title="Declaring variables inside a switch statement - Stack Overflow" href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1231198/declaring-variables-inside-a-switch-statement/1231209#1231209">an answer given to a Stack Overflow question regarding an odd Objective-C compiler error</a>.&#160; The answer seemed to allude to a language specification somewhere that doesn’t allow variable declarations in one-liner embedded statements of control structures (loops, <font face="Courier New">switch</font> statements, <font face="Courier New">if-else</font> statements, etc.).&#160; Not only that, Objective-C wasn’t unique in this restriction; it appears Java and even C itself have had this restriction for quite a while as well.</p>  <p>Naturally this got my curiosity going and I decided to see if C# had also carried over such a restriction.&#160; The answer is yes; it appears that Java, C#, and Objective-C have all kept this language restriction from their common ancestor C.&#160; Let’s get right to what it looks like:</p> <span class='fullpost'> <p><a href="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_rps657FzHZ0/SrqdKFwyBLI/AAAAAAAAADA/8fajE6RTF0o/s1600-h/code_screenshot%5B6%5D.png"><img style="border-right-width: 0px; display: inline; border-top-width: 0px; border-bottom-width: 0px; border-left-width: 0px" title="code_screenshot" border="0" alt="code_screenshot" src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_rps657FzHZ0/SrqdKaU74uI/AAAAAAAAADE/HGin3AOsrsM/code_screenshot_thumb%5B4%5D.png?imgmax=800" width="416" height="712" /></a> </p>  <p>The red-underlined errors read “<font face="Courier New">embedded statement cannot be a declaration or labeled statement</font>” and the green-underlined warnings read “<font face="Courier New">the variable ‘i’ is assigned but its value is never used</font>.”&#160; You’ve probably seen the warning quite a few times before, but the compiler error really caught me by surprise.&#160; I mean it makes sense that declaring a variable in the one-line body of a control structure is pointless, as it would immediately go out of scope (and usefulness) after declared.&#160; But I thought it odd for the compiler to actually deny such a program statement, as if it put the compiler in an invalid state or maybe it was somehow dangerous.</p>  <p>One thing I do want to point out that appears to be different from the other languages (or at the very least Objective-C) is that the variable declaration is allowed in the <font face="Courier New">switch</font> statement, as illustrated in the image above.</p>  <p>To figure out why this isn’t allowed, I decided to actually look into the <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/vcsharp/aa336809.aspx">C# 3.0 Language Specification</a> to see if there were any comments or explanations regarding this issue.&#160; I ended up finding the C# language grammar in Appendix B.&#160; I was able to parse through the grammar and find this restriction in the grammar itself.&#160; Take a look:</p>  <p><strong>B.2.5 </strong><a name="_Toc174237894"><strong>Statements</strong></a></p>  <div><em>statement: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px"><em>labeled-statement      <br />declaration-statement       <br />embedded-statement</em></div>  <p></p>  <div><em>embedded-statement: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px"><em>block      <br />empty-statement       <br />expression-statement       <br />selection-statement       <br />iteration-statement       <br />jump-statement       <br />try-statement       <br />checked-statement       <br />unchecked-statement       <br />lock-statement       <br />using-statement       <br />yield-statement</em></div>  <p></p>  <div><em>block: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px">{<em> statement-list<sub>optional</sub></em> }</div>  <p></p>  <div><em>statement-list: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px"><em>statement      <br />statement-list statement</em></div>  <p>...</p>  <div><em>selection-statement: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px"><em>if-statement      <br />switch-statement</em></div>  <p></p>  <div><em>if-statement: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px">if ( <em>boolean-expression</em> ) <em>embedded-statement</em>     <br />if ( <em>boolean-expression</em> ) <em>embedded-statement</em> else <em>embedded-statement</em></div>  <p></p>  <div><em>switch-statement: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px">switch ( <em>expression</em> ) <em>switch-block</em></div>  <p></p>  <div><em>switch-block: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px">{ <em>switch-sections<sub>optional</sub></em> }</div>  <p></p>  <div><em>switch-sections: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px"><em>switch-section      <br />switch-sections switch-section</em></div>  <p></p>  <div><em>switch-section: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px"><em>switch-labels statement-list</em></div>  <p></p>  <div><em>switch-labels: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px"><em>switch-label      <br />switch-labels switch-label</em></div>  <p></p>  <div><em>switch-label: </em></div>  <div style="margin-left: 40px">case <em>constant-expression</em> :     <br />default :</div>  <p>...</p>  <p>You’ll notice that there is the concept of a <font face="Courier New">statement</font> and an <font face="Courier New">embedded-statement</font>; also note that <font face="Courier New">statement</font> is a superset of <font face="Courier New">embedded-statement</font>, adding two other types of statements: <font face="Courier New">labeled-statement</font> and <font face="Courier New">declaration-statement</font>.&#160; If a particular grammar rule requires an <font face="Courier New">embedded-statement</font>, then those two latter types of statements are not allowed in that context.&#160; If we wanted to allow those two statement types, our grammar rule should specify the generic <font face="Courier New">statement</font> category instead.</p>  <p>Also noteworthy is that an <font face="Courier New">embedded-statement</font> can resolve to a <font face="Courier New">block</font>, which includes braces around a <font face="Courier New">statement-list</font>.&#160; A <font face="Courier New">statement-list</font> is one or more <font face="Courier New">statement</font> entities, which would now allow us to use the two statement types excluded from <font face="Courier New">embedded-statement</font>.</p>  <p>Something interesting that is not included in the grammar snippet above, the following statement constructs (and language keywords) require the <font face="Courier New">block</font> statement construct, bypassing the option of a grammar resolution to <font face="Courier New">embedded-statement</font> directly and allowing you to leave off surrounding braces: <font face="Courier New">try</font>, <font face="Courier New">catch</font>, <font face="Courier New">finally</font>, <font face="Courier New">checked</font>, and <font face="Courier New">unchecked</font>.</p>  <p>Almost all of the other statement constructs allow you the option of a one-liner <font face="Courier New">embedded-statement</font> (or which can be resolved into a <font face="Courier New">block</font>), including <font face="Courier New">if</font>, <font face="Courier New">if-else</font>, <font face="Courier New">while</font>, <font face="Courier New">do-while</font>, <font face="Courier New">for</font>, and <font face="Courier New">foreach</font>.&#160; The one surprising exception is the <font face="Courier New">switch</font> construct, which allows for a <font face="Courier New">statement-list</font> after each <font face="Courier New">switch-label</font>.&#160; As a side note, this allows you to put useless braces (via <font face="Courier New">block</font>) around your <font face="Courier New">statement-list</font> (or anywhere inside it) after any of your <font face="Courier New">switch-label</font> statements if you wanted.&#160; But back to the point, these facts explain the existence of (and in one case, lack of) compiler errors regarding embedded statements in the code screenshot near the top.</p>  <p>Now you will know exactly what the compiler means when it gives you the error that an “<font face="Courier New">embedded statement cannot be a declaration or labeled statement.</font>”</p> </span>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
