<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Active Directory | Mike Murray]]></title>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/categories/active-directory/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-03T19:32:09-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mkmurray.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Murray]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adding a Linux Machine to a Windows Domain]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2008/07/14/adding-a-linux-machine-to-a-windows-domain/"/>
    <updated>2008-07-14T14:26:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2008/07/14/adding-a-linux-machine-to-a-windows-domain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Before I went on vacation last week, I was able to successfully add a Red Hat Enterprise Server (version 3) box to our Windows 2003 Active Directory Domain.&#160; I primarily used the following link as a guide through the process:</p>  <p><a title="http://www.wlug.org.nz/ActiveDirectorySamba" href="http://www.wlug.org.nz/ActiveDirectorySamba">http://www.wlug.org.nz/ActiveDirectorySamba</a></p>  <p>I will now add some extra commentary to each of the steps on the tutorial for my specific situation:</p> <span class='fullpost'> <p>--------------------------------------------------</p>  <p><strong>1.&#160; Install and Check Necessary Packages</strong>:&#160; For this step, I opened a shell and used the <font face="Courier New">up2date</font> utility to verify the named packages were up-to-date.&#160; Prior to this, I had let Red Hat update everything it thought needed to be updated; this means that this step was trivial for me, since every necessary package was found and up-to-date.&#160; Also, my installation had <font face="Courier New">system-config-samba</font> for the first packaged named in the list.</p>  <p><strong>2.&#160; Configure Name Resolution</strong>:&#160; We chose the easier option of merely configuring the <font face="Courier New">hosts</font> file on both machines.&#160; I know the tutorial says to avoid it, but we are not at a place right now where we could easily switch our DNS machine to be a Linux box.&#160; We haven't had any problems so far, but I will keep you updated.</p>  <p><strong>3.&#160; Configure Samba and Winbindd</strong>:&#160; I went ahead and just replaced my <font face="Courier New">smb.conf</font> with the one in the tutorial and then modified the <font face="Courier New">workgroup</font>, <font face="Courier New">netbios name</font>, <font face="Courier New">realm</font>, and <font face="Courier New">password server</font> accordingly.</p>  <p><strong>4.&#160; Configure Kerberos</strong>:&#160; I was able to get the <font face="Courier New">net ads join</font> command to work after changing one configuration setting in the <font face="Courier New">\etc\krb5.conf</font> file (and therefore, not needing to perform the &quot;<font face="Courier New">Manual Approach</font>&quot;).&#160; I changed the <font face="Courier New">dns_lookup_kdc</font> property to <font face="Courier New">true</font> and then the Domain server was able to accept the Linux box into the domain.&#160; I eventually ended up making a few more changes to this file after seeing an example file on Red Hat's support site.&#160; My config file looks just like the one at this link, with the exception of the property I set to <font face="Courier New">true</font> mentioned above (also don't forget to replace the <font face="Courier New">EXAMPLE.DIRECTORY</font> and <font face="Courier New">10.0.0.1</font> place-holders with your specific values):</p>  <p><a title="http://kbase.redhat.com/faq/FAQ_71_2338.shtm" href="http://kbase.redhat.com/faq/FAQ_71_2338.shtm">http://kbase.redhat.com/faq/FAQ_71_2338.shtm</a></p>  <p>Next, go ahead and execute the commands in the &quot;<font face="Courier New">(Re)starting Samba and Winbindd</font>&quot; section in order to test that everything is playing nice.&#160; For my installation, however, in order to restart the Samba service, I used the following command from a shell:</p>  <p><font face="Courier New">/etc/rc.d/init.d/smb restart</font></p>  <p>If everything goes alright, then modify the <font face="Courier New">init.d</font> startup scripts in order to start the <font face="Courier New">smb</font> and <font face="Courier New">winbindd</font> services at boot up.&#160; For my installation, I ended up just using the GUI utility provided by Red Hat found under something like<font face="Courier New"> System Settings<font face="Verdana"> |</font> Server Settings</font> | <font face="Courier New">Services</font><font face="Verdana"> (or you can just type <font face="Courier New">redhat-config-services </font>into a shell).</font>&#160; Just check the two services and then be sure to hit the <font face="Courier New">Save</font> button.</p>  <p><strong>5.&#160; Configure PAM and Winbind</strong>:&#160; For this step, I ended up changing a few different config files, and I'm not which ones really mattered or not.&#160; So go ahead and make the changes to <font face="Courier New">\etc\pam.d\login</font>; I believe it is 3 lines that need to be added (the <font face="Courier New">auth</font> line for <font face="Courier New">pam_unix.so</font> and two <font face="Courier New">pam_winbind.so</font> lines, one for the <font face="Courier New">auth</font> section and one for the <font face="Courier New">account</font><font face="Verdana"> section).&#160; I also added these same 3 lines to <font face="Courier New">\etc\pam.d\remote</font> and <font face="Courier New">\etc\pam.d\sshd</font>.&#160; For the <font face="Courier New">\etc\pam.d\su</font> config file, I only added the two <font face="Courier New">pam_winbind.so</font> lines (with no parameters and using the <font face="Courier New">/lib/security/$ISA/</font> folder structure all of the other lines in the file use).</font></p>  <p>There is one more change I made to <font face="Courier New">\etc\pam.d\system-auth</font>, which allows the automatic creation of user profiles for your domain accounts upon first login.&#160; I added the following script call as <font face="Courier New">required</font> under the <font face="Courier New">session</font> section:</p>  <p><font face="Courier New">/lib/security/$ISA/pam_mkhomedir.so skel=/etc/skel umask=0077</font></p>  <p><font face="Verd">Be sure to read the article at the following link to understand what this script will and won't do:</font></p>  <p><a title="http://kbase.redhat.com/faq/FAQ_85_5367.shtm" href="http://kbase.redhat.com/faq/FAQ_85_5367.shtm">http://kbase.redhat.com/faq/FAQ_85_5367.shtm</a></p>  <p>--------------------------------------------------</p>  <p>After verifying that domain user accounts can login, su, and ssh, I also did a reboot to make sure everything started up correctly on boot up and that the profiles were being automatically created.&#160; Also, make sure the login screen will show the box name and it's newly inherited domain.</p>  <p>I may be trying to do this exact same procedure soon for an Ubuntu machine on our company network.&#160; I'm still undecided whether to just try this method above or to try following a pretty well-written tutorial I found on Ubuntu's support site (currently, I'm leaning toward the latter).&#160; I'll let you know how it goes when I do though.</p>  <p><strong><u>FOLLOWUP (07/16/08)</u></strong>:&#160; I just found out the Ubuntu machine is going to be phased out and redone anyway.&#160; So I won't be attempting to migrate it to our Windows Domain anymore.&#160; But here are some good links I found in my research specific to doing this process on Ubuntu:</p>  <ul>   <li><a title="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/ActiveDirectoryWinbindHowto" href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/ActiveDirectoryWinbindHowto">https://help.ubuntu.com/community/ActiveDirectoryWinbindHowto</a></li>    <li><a title="http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=5409" href="http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=5409">http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=5409</a></li>    <li><a title="http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=113149" href="http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=113149">http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=113149</a></li> </ul> </span>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>PapaBear</div>
<div class='content'>
Excellent!  Now if only my current company had some linux servers for me to play around on (and were willing to let me play with their Active Directory).  Someday I plan to buy a really beefy 64bit server (one running the new cell processor), put windows server 2008 on it and virtualize a whole bunch of windows and linux machines in an isolated network on it.  Then I can designate one of the many windows server 2003 virtual machines that I will have running in it as a D.C. and try to join every other virtual machine to it (including the linux ones using the steps you outlined here!) all on a single physical machine (one of the virtual machines will be a linux firewall/router so that I can connect to the host machine's network adapter so that it can see the internet).   Someday....  Until then I can only dream about the awesome experience you are having at your current job.  Kudos, Mike!</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
