<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: F# | Mike Murray]]></title>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/categories/f-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-10T15:43:46-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://mkmurray.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Murray]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[F# Pipeline Operator in C#?]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/09/06/f-pipeline-operator-in-c/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-06T20:22:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/09/06/f-pipeline-operator-in-c</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I am currently reading the <a href="http://www.manning.com/petricek/" target="_blank">Real-World Functional Programming</a> book from <a href="http://www.manning.com/" target="_blank">Manning Publications</a>. It’s mostly an exercise in learning F#, but also to improve my C# code as well. I finally learned what the F# pipelining operator (<font face="Courier New">|&gt;</font>) is all about, and I was so impressed I thought I would try to figure out how to bring it into C# if possible.</p> <span class="fullpost">   <h3>Introducing the F# Pipeline Operator</h3>    <p>Here is some F# code that defines a list of integers and a pair of functions.&#160; They are then used in a few “higher-order” functions (functions that utilize other functions as parameters or return values, according to my book).&#160; <font face="courier new">List.filter</font> is equivalent to the LINQ <font face="Courier New">IEnumerable.Where()</font> extension method, and <font face="Courier New">List.map</font> is equivalent to <font face="Courier New">IEnumerable.Select()</font>.</p>    <pre class="brush: csharp">let numbers = [ 1 .. 10 ]
let isOdd(n) = n % 2 = 1
let square(n) = n * n

List.filter isOdd numbers
List.map square (List.filter isOdd numbers)</pre>

  <p>The interesting part is the last line of code, where it is argued that you lose a little bit of code readability because the function that is actually executed first (<font face="Courier New">List.filter</font>) is found second in the expression statement.&#160; Enter the F# pipelining operator:</p>

  <pre class="brush: csharp">let squared =
  numbers
  |&gt; List.filter isOdd
  |&gt; List.map square</pre>

  <p>Even though we’re no longer a compact, one-liner expression, I think we’ve gained some code readability.&#160; It says to take the list <font face="Courier New">numbers</font> and perform the following manipulations in the exact order listed.&#160; Cool stuff, if I say so myself.</p>

  <h3>“There is No Charge for Awesomeness…or Attractiveness”</h3>

  <p>(Sorry, I’ve been watching the movie <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0441773/" target="_blank">Kung Fu Panda</a> a lot with my kids lately.&#160; Funny stuff.)&#160; So can this awesomeness be brought over into C#?&#160; I opened up Visual Studio and tried to see if I could figure out how to define my own operator or reuse one of the existing ones.</p>

  <p>I realize C# is a pretty tough language to flip keywords and operators around and invent new syntax with (ok, it’s impossible), but I tried anyway.&#160; The type of code readability issue I wanted to remedy is the same as with the F# code snippet above.&#160; I thought it would be nice to make C# code like the following statement more readable and digestible (especially the execution order):</p>

  <pre class="brush: csharp">Convert.ToInt32(Context.Request[“requestParam”].Trim());</pre>

  <p>As I started to (unsuccessfully) beat out some pretty rough code, I ran into problems with trying to make extension methods that are operator definition overloads and errors saying “<font face="Courier New">One of the parameters of a binary operator must be the containing type.</font>”&#160; It just wasn’t working and then I began to realize that C# already has a pipelining syntax, even if only in one small subset of the .NET API.&#160; You can find a decent pipelining syntax with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fluent_interface" target="_blank">Fluent Interface</a> used for the LINQ extension methods.&#160; Its power is in the fact that the functions return the object type that was passed in and acted upon, so that more functions can be chained on afterward in a composable manner.&#160; The ability to do things like <font face="Courier New">collection.Where().Select().OrderBy()</font> is a much more declarative and functional solution to imperative <font face="Courier New">for</font> loops (and it makes it more readable and intention revealing in my opinion).&#160; It’s a difference in describing more <u><em>what</em></u> you want to be accomplished rather than <em><u>how</u></em> it is to be accomplished (especially when the <u><em>how</em></u> in programming languages is more readable to a computer than it is a human).</p>

  <p>So the good news is that you indeed can have a nice pipelining syntax in C#, especially for APIs that are designed with Fluent Interfaces like LINQ.&#160; However, it doesn’t solve code readability issues with code snippets like the C# fragment I showed above.&#160; For those regular, non-fluent method calls in the rest of the .NET API, you must use old-fashioned Object-Oriented Programming practices of breaking code up into meaningful, atomic units of statements and naming and encapsulating functions cohesively in order to get more readable code.</p>
</span>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jonas Elfström</div>
<div class='content'>
This looks a whole lot like the Thrush Combinator.<br /><a href="http://alicebobandmallory.com/articles/2009/10/06/the-thrush-combinator-in-c" rel="nofollow">I implemented</a> that one in C# a while ago</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Richard Beauchamp</div>
<div class='content'>
This comment has been removed by the author.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mike Murray</div>
<div class='content'>
Funny you should mention the Maybe Monad, as I&#39;ve been looking into Monads off and on for several months trying to figure out how I could use them in everyday code.  I likely will be posting something on this in the somewhat near future.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Just a small hint from someone who uses something like this in productive code on a day-to-day basis:<br /><br />Take your time and extend the static methods a bit. It won&#39;t hurt to build something like a maybe-monad in there.<br /><br />You know - check if the input is null and return null if so.<br /><br />For this you need either:<br />- &quot;where U : class&quot;<br />- use Equals<br /><br />For the same reason I give somethink like a &quot;DefaultValue&quot; Funktion that checks the input for null and responses with the default-value if so, if not it will give the original value.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mike Murray</div>
<div class='content'>
Very intriguing! Man I wish I had thought about that.  I suppose I&#39;m still new to designing APIs that pass around Funcs.<br /><br />I was able to make the following code work with the type inference (and without having to specify the types to the Then method):<br /><br />var blah = &quot;576 &quot;<br />.Then(x =&gt; x.Trim())<br />.Then(x =&gt; Convert.ToInt32(x));<br /><br />Not too bad really.  A little too much C# syntax though, but I&#39;d argue it might be more readable than what we started with, the code everyone writes.  It appears my code snippet doesn&#39;t even need the second extension method.<br /><br />Thanks for sharing!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Yusuf Motara</div>
<div class='content'>
You could try this:<br /><br />static class Extn {<br />    public static U Then&lt;T,U&gt;(this T o, Func&lt;T, U&gt; f) { return f(o); }<br />    public static U Then&lt;T, U&gt;(this T o, Func&lt;T, Func&lt;U&gt;&gt; fe) { return fe(o)(); }<br />}<br /><br />... which lets you write the more-readable:<br /><br />var blah = &quot;576  &quot;<br />   .Then&lt;string,string&gt;(x =&gt; x.Trim)<br />   .Then(Convert.ToInt32);<br /><br />Unfortunately, it seems that you need to make the generic parameters explicit; C#&#39;s type inference is nowhere near as good as F#&#39;s.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
