<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Self-Improvement | Mike Murray]]></title>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/categories/self-improvement/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-08T21:27:17-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://mkmurray.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Murray]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Well-Rounded Developers]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2012/11/17/well-rounded-developers/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-17T19:32:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2012/11/17/well-rounded-developers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had the opportunity this week to talk with some terrific Computer Science
students nearing graduation and who were beginning to look for employment. It
provided me the chance to put into words the amazing culture and environment
that exists at my workplace. The software development team at <a href="https://www.extendhealth.com/">Extend
Health</a> is second to none in both talent and
passion for creating clean, modular code that is maintainable because of its
extensibility. Everyone on the team contributes and has a trusted voice. It
truly is an environment I've never seen before and am certainly proud to be
apart of.</p>

<p>One of the main things that hit me while talking to these graduating students
was how well-rounded our developers have come. No, I'm not talking about the
amount of soda and treats we consume. I'm referring to the varying skills each
one of us have developed. From front-end to back-end or web sites to desktop
apps, every single member of the team is capable of jumping into any of our
codebases and tackling new features or bugs with a excellent degree of
competentcy. I find this fascinating because it is not the norm at many medium
to large size companies. It is typical for a developer to be hired to a
position or team where he or she works on a single project and codebase for a
few years until they get bored enough to change positions within the company or
go somewhere else completely. This has not been the case for all of the
developers at Extend Health.</p>

<p>We are currently divided into four teams of about four or five devs each. While
each team may have past experience with a certain project or codebase, they are
not automatically the chosen team to work on it again the next time. Because of
this, there is shared knowledge across teams and team members, instead of all
the knowledge residing in only one person's head. This avoids the "what if
someone gets hit by a bus" problem <a href="http://rhauert.wordpress.com/2012/11/17/the-bus-factor/">my coworker Ryan just blogged
about</a>. The other side
effect is that our developers have all become well-rounded in varying languages
and platforms, solving both front-end and back-end problems. Contrast this with
how I used to classify my dev skill set four or five years ago before working
at Extend Health. I used to consider myself a back-end systems developer,
feeling it was important to have specialization in order to differentiate myself
and provide a chance to develop focused and in-depth experience. I also fooled
myself into thinking that I preferred this designation because web development
was trivial and only the hardest and most worthwhile problems were in the
back-end systems. Instead, I merely lacked some meaningful experience with
front-end web development, which is harder to come by in the typical work
enivronment I described above. However in my current employment, I've become a
much more well-rounded software developer.</p>

<p>I'm not entirely positive if our environment and team dynamic were
intentionally setup to ensure we were all well-rounded developers (though every
other good aspect of our dev culture seems to have been carefully pieced
together by <a href="http://coreykaylor.com/">Corey</a>). Regardless, I am appreciatevly
taking note of the advantageous results of such a configuration. This is one
very important aspect of true job satisfaction and also in avoiding high
turnover and attrition in workforce.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
