<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Web | Mike Murray]]></title>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/categories/web/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-10T15:57:48-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://mkmurray.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Murray]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FubuMVC Webinar - Compositional and Convention-based Web Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/07/21/fubumvc-webinar-compositional-and-convention-based-web-development/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-21T12:44:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/07/21/fubumvc-webinar-compositional-and-convention-based-web-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I just gave a webinar yesterday for <a href="http://www.jpboodhoo.com/">JP Boodhoo’s</a> <a href="http://webinars.developwithpassion.com/">Develop With Passion® webinar series</a> on Compositional and Convention-based Web Development with <a href="http://fubumvc.com/">FubuMVC</a>. The recorded session is now posted online with a slew of referenced and related links. I apologize for the sound quality and will make corrections if I get another chance to do another webinar/screencast. Here is the link to the recording:</p>  <p><a href="http://webinars.developwithpassion.com/webinars/3">http://webinars.developwithpassion.com/webinars/3</a></p>  <p>I didn’t mention this in the screencast but before we began switching our company’s production website to FubuMVC, we first devised a way to get the benefit of <a href="http://murrayon.net/2011/06/fubumvc-behavior-chains-bmvc-pattern.html">FubuMVC Behavior Chains</a> while still on the ASP.NET MVC framework. Please feel free to read more about that successful venture at <a href="http://paceyourself.net/">Bob Pace’s</a> <a href="http://paceyourself.net/2011/06/11/mvctofubu---transition-your-website-from-aspnet-mvc-to-fubumvc-part-1/">blog post on the MvcToFubu project</a>.</p>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FubuMVC Behavior Chains - The BMVC Pattern]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/06/13/fubumvc-behavior-chains-the-bmvc-pattern/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-13T16:01:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/06/13/fubumvc-behavior-chains-the-bmvc-pattern</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>For the last several months at work, we have been gradually migrating our production website to use the .NET open source <a href="http://fubumvc.com/" target="_blank">FubuMVC web framework</a>. Before committing to a whole new infrastructure for our site, some brilliant talent on our team decided to improve our experience on the ASP.NET MVC framework by integrating in one of FubuMVC’s most compelling features, behavior chains. <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/bob_pace" target="_blank">Bob Pace</a> originally blogged about the process in a two part blog post series (<a href="http://paceyourself.net/2010/08/06/integrating-fubumvc-with-aspnet-mvc-part-1/" target="_blank">part 1</a> and <a href="http://paceyourself.net/2010/08/13/integrating-fubumvc-with-aspnet-mvc-part-2/" target="_blank">part 2</a>); since then, he has <a href="https://github.com/bobpace/MvcToFubu" target="_blank">created a packaged solution called MvcToFubu</a> which he <a href="http://paceyourself.net/2011/06/11/mvctofubu---transition-your-website-from-aspnet-mvc-to-fubumvc-part-1/" target="_blank">just recently started another blog post series about</a>.</p>  <p>Behavior chains are by far my favorite feature of FubuMVC. I believe they single-handedly revolutionized our use of the MVC pattern in a web environment. In fact, I like to think of it as a whole new pattern, the <strong>BMVC Pattern</strong> (I was told by a coworker that the ‘B’ should stand for “Better”, and while that’s true, I’ll stick with “Behaviors”). No, I’m not sincerely trying to coin yet another design or architectural pattern buzzword. However, I am most sincerely not joking when I say behavior chains add a whole new dimension to how I design web architectures. I find myself creating composable pipelines of cohesive, testable components in lieu of monolithic controllers and actions.</p> <span class="fullpost">   <h3>What are Behavior Chains?</h3>    <p>Have you ever looked at your controller actions and thought “Man, there’s a lot going on here!” (validation, authorization, transactions, ORM setup, logging, caching, etc.)? If you haven’t, I urge you to take a conscious look at your controller actions and try to identify code that doesn’t <u>directly</u> relate to the purpose of the page (or sub-view of the page). Shouldn’t there be a way to move some of this secondary infrastructure code out of our controller actions and have it be applied conventionally to the correct actions/routes? Yes, and this is exactly what Behavior Chains are meant to accomplish, the ability to create composable pipelines of reusable behavior nodes for each route in your site.</p>    <p>Behavior chains can be built up in any order you want for each route via Conventions and Policies, which are extension points that allow you to inspect and modify the entire Behavior Graph that was built by FubuMVC during startup bootstrapping. The behavior graph is the modifiable collection of all behavior chains in the site, initially built with just a few default behavior nodes for each route. A typical behavior chain by default usually has an ActionCall node (representing the call to a controller action) and an Output node (often a tie-in to a view rendering engine, but can also be JSON or anything else). Other behavior nodes can be sprinkled into the pipeline in any order in front of or in between the ActionCall and the Output nodes. As mentioned before via the use of Conventions and Policies, it is common practice to filter your list of behavior chains using LINQ extension methods and then add a specific behavior node into the matching chains at a specific location in the chain. This truly elevates coding to conventions to a new level; some of the filtering criteria regarding controller actions that you may come up with could be as follows:</p>    <ul>     <li>Action method names that contain a certain word. </li>      <li>Actions methods that are located in a particular controller or namespace. </li>      <li>Action method signatures that contain an input/output model that implements a specific interface. </li>      <li>Action method signatures that contain an input/output model that contains a property of a certain type or have a particular C# attribute applied to it. </li>      <li>So on, so forth…whatever you can dream up! </li>   </ul>    <p>One more aspect of behavior chains that is important to point out is the logistics in how behavior nodes are chained together. The chains are not merely a linked-list of behavior nodes that are traversed linearly. Instead the makeup of the chains is better conceptualized to be an outer behavior node wrapping around an inner behavior node, which is then itself an outer node wrapped around another inner node, and so on. In fact, the FubuMVC developers like to refer to this chaining architecture as the Onion Layer Model or the Russian Doll Model (conjuring up a mental image of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matryoshka_doll">nesting Russian doll toy called a matryoshka doll or a babushka doll</a>). When an outer behavior node has finished executing it’s logic, it can then optionally execute it’s inner behavior node logic (or stop the behavior chain entirely in order to return early with a response, an error, or even transfer to a different route and behavior chain). One of the key advantages that this wrapping architecture can afford is the ability for an outer behavior to run additional logic or clean up code after all inner behavior nodes have completed (i.e., transactions can be committed, connections can be closed, sessions can be disposed, etc.).</p>    <h3>How does this change the way I code my controllers?</h3>    <p>I find that my controller actions are much thinner and more focused on the base case and the successful code path. All the exceptional code paths and edge cases have been identified and deal with by the other behavior nodes in the chain, prior to my action call being invoked. My action call can now focus on the essential logic that differentiate this route from others. That essential logic doesn’t get lost anymore in the necessary infrastructure code that should be a secondary concern. And all of this logic can be broken up into cohesive, reusable components within a flexible request/response pipeline that can be built up automatically by coding to whatever conventions you deem beneficial. Behavior chains really do add a whole new first-class citizen to the MVC design pattern. Do yourself a favor and check out the MvcToFubu solution mentioned at the top of this post, and bring some FubuMVC behavior chain goodness to your ASP.NET MVC website. I think you might be as impressed as we were and yearn for <a href="http://lostechies.com/chadmyers/2011/05/30/cool-stuff-in-fubucore-and-fubumvc-series/">the other killer features of FubuMVC</a> as well.</p> </span>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mike Murray</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks for thought! Perhaps I&#39;ll post on the mailing list and see what others think about it being involved in the FubuMVC documentation somewhere.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Rex</div>
<div class='content'>
Great post, I didn&#39;t see this one when I was writing my post about authentication behavior. This is a great explanation of behavior chains in FubuMVC.<br /><br />This would also be a great intro to behaviors for the fubumvc guides.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Web Deployment Tool]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/09/29/web-deployment-tool/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-29T17:45:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/09/29/web-deployment-tool</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>It appears that the IIS team at Microsoft has officially completed a 1.0 version of the deployment utility I mentioned at the end of <a title="Visual Studio Web Deployment Projects" href="http://murrayon.net/2008/02/visual-studio-web-deployment-projects.html">my previous post about Visual Studio Web Deployment Projects</a> almost two years ago.&#160; It includes a command-line tool named MSDeploy that helps with deploying and syncing web projects across all of the web servers in your server farm.&#160; The installation also includes all kinds of packaging and deployment features that seem really handy.&#160; You can even do migrations from IIS 6 to IIS 7 or package your apps to be distributed via the <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/web/downloads/platform.aspx">Microsoft Web Platform Installer</a>.</p>  <p>I thought that maybe the tool creates MSI installers, but it appears the package may actually just be a ZIP file that you can import and export through the IIS Manager or various other command-line tools or PowerShell Cmdlets.</p>  <p>Here is the page where you can read more about the toolset and download the installer:&#160; <a title="http://www.iis.net/extensions/WebDeploymentTool" href="http://www.iis.net/extensions/WebDeploymentTool">http://www.iis.net/extensions/WebDeploymentTool</a></p>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ASP.NET Profile and Web Application Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/02/11/asp-net-profile-and-web-application-projects/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-11T15:08:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/02/11/asp-net-profile-and-web-application-projects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I talked at length about the ASP.NET <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provider_model">Provider Model pattern</a> and the ease of implementing several built-in services you can have for free with ASP.NET 2.0 in <a title="ASP.NET Providers - Membership, Role, and Profile" href="http://murrayon.net/2009/01/aspnet-providers-membership-role-and.html">my previous series of posts</a>.&#160; In this post, I will be discussing a few issues I ran into using the Profile system with the <font face="Courier New">Web Application</font> project template instead of the <font face="Courier New">Web Site</font> project template as found in Visual Studio's list of default project templates.</p>  <p>The crux of the issue is that Visual Studio doesn't automatically generate the <font face="Courier New">Profile</font> proxy class object when using the <font face="Courier New">Web Application</font> project template, like it does with the <font face="Courier New">Web Site</font> project template.&#160; This proxy class can be used to obtain access to strongly-typed properties representing the custom Profile fields you specified in your <font face="Courier New">Web.config</font>.&#160; This is a very convenient way to access a user's Profile data, both for authenticated and for anonymous users.</p>  <p>Let's discuss the issue a little further and then I will present a workaround that I found and have successfully implemented in my own project.</p> <span class='fullpost'> <h3>VS Project Templates:&#160; Web Site vs. Web Application</h3>  <p>It appears that Microsoft has tried to differentiate these two project templates as much as possible in Visual Studio 2008.&#160; In 2005, you would go to the <font face="Courier New">New Project</font> dialog window and you would see these two <font face="Courier New">Web</font> project templates side-by-side, wondering what difference it would make if you chose one over the other.&#160; However, in Visual Studio 2008, it appears they reworked this whole dialog and menu system for starting a new project so that you would never see these two project templates side-by-side.&#160; In 2008, you have more than one option in the <font face="Courier New">File</font> menu for starting a project; those options are <font face="Courier New">File | New | Project</font> and <font face="Courier New">File | New | Web Site</font>.&#160; The first option is the one that will get you to the <font face="Courier New">ASP.NET Web Application</font> template, while the second takes you to the <font face="Courier New">ASP.NET Web Site</font> project template.</p>  <p>Now as for the differences between these two templates, I'll outline a few of the main differences and give a little bit of history of how these two templates came to coexist.&#160; The history in a nutshell is that Visual Studio 2005 came out with the <font face="Courier New">Web Site</font> project template to replace the old, but proven project configuration used by ASP.NET 1.x.&#160; In the opinion of many, the old template better encouraged Object-Oriented design practices.&#160; The new template had no project file for explicitly delineating what files where included in the project and namespacing was quite cumbersome, as the only painless design was to let everything pile up into one big default namespace.&#160; A few other changes involved taking ASP.NET back to compiling on the fly at the web server and also drastically changing the organization of UI template and code-behind files.&#160; It appears the intention was to closely mimic the configuration and deployment practices of popular agile languages like PHP and Ruby on Rails.</p>  <p>In the Service Pack 1 of Visual Studio 2005, Microsoft decided to resurrect the older project template under the name of <font face="Courier New">Web Application</font>.&#160; There is evidence to suggest that Microsoft considers this latter project template an &quot;enterprise&quot; project type, as compared to the casual <font face="Courier New">Web Site</font> project template.&#160; With the advent of Visual Studio 2008, it is apparent that Microsoft is committed to supporting both project types for at least a little while.&#160; For a more detailed discussion of the history and differences of these two project templates, I suggest the following blog post by <a href="http://reddnet.net/code/">Stephen M. Redd</a>:</p>  <ul>   <li><a href="http://reddnet.net/code/aspnet-web-site-vs-web-application/">ASP.NET - Web Site vs. Web Application</a></li> </ul>  <h3>Web Profile Builder by Joe Wrobel</h3>  <p>The ability to retrieve and update your custom Profile fields at design time via strongly-typed properties on the <font face="Courier New">Profile</font> proxy class is extremely convenient.&#160; Unfortunately, you get no such compiler and intellisense love if you are using the <font face="Courier New">Web Application</font> project template for your site.</p>  <p>In trying to find a workaround, I came across a <a title="Web Profile Builder for Web Application Projects" href="http://weblogs.asp.net/joewrobel/archive/2008/02/03/web-profile-builder-for-web-application-projects.aspx">blog post by Joe Wrobel introducing a project he worked on to solve this issue</a>.&#160; It's called the <font face="Courier New">Web Profile Builder</font> (here's a <a title="Web Profile Builder" href="http://code.msdn.microsoft.com/WebProfileBuilder/Release/ProjectReleases.aspx">link to it's project page on MSDN Code Gallery</a>) and it was based on a project called the <a href="http://www.codeplex.com/WebProfile">Web Profile Generator</a>, which was a Visual Studio 2005 Add-In project found on <a href="http://www.codeplex.com/">CodePlex</a>.&#160; The latter project seems to have not been worked on in over a year and a half, nor does it seem to be compatible with Visual Studio 2008.&#160; Hence, Joe feeling the need to start up on his own project, with a few improvements on the side of course.</p>  <p>In Joe's introductory post to the project, he mentions he changed the Visual Studio integration from being a plug-in to being an MSBuild Build Task.&#160; The method for incorporating the Build Task into your project is to add a line into your project file (the one with file extension <font face="Courier New">.csproj</font>).&#160; In case you weren't aware, Visual Studio project files are just <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MSBuild">MSBuild</a> build scripts.&#160; For details about where to put this line in the file (and about a message Visual Studio pops up when it detects you've mucked with the project file), be sure to check out <a title="Web Profile Builder for Web Application Projects" href="http://weblogs.asp.net/joewrobel/archive/2008/02/03/web-profile-builder-for-web-application-projects.aspx">Joe's post on the Web Profile Builder project</a>.</p>  <p>There are a couple of other things I need to point out about using the Build Task that weren't entirely clear to me beforehand.&#160; The build task actually generates a C# code file that is intended to be included into your project; once it's generated, you need to go to the <font face="Courier New">Solution Explorer</font> and explicitly add it as a file in your project (one way is through the <font face="Courier New">Add | Existing Item</font> menu option).&#160; One of the main things that helped me decide to use this solution and how to configure it was reading two blog posts from <a href="http://www.codersbarn.com/">Anthony Grace</a>; the second post below has a great excerpt apparently from the <font face="Courier New">Web Profile Builder</font> documentation that explains the process I outlined above in a bit more detail:</p>  <ul>   <li><a href="http://www.codersbarn.com/post/2008/06/ASPNET-Web-Site-versus-Web-Application-Project.aspx">ASP.NET: Web Site versus Web Application Project</a></li>    <li><a href="http://www.codersbarn.com/post/2008/07/10/ASPNET-PayPal-Subscriptions-IPN.aspx">ASP.NET PayPal Subscription IPN</a></li> </ul>  <p>Also, it is not necessary to do the steps in the <font face="Courier New">Extended Usage</font> section of Joe's blog post.&#160; They are optional configuration points in the <font face="Courier New">Web.config</font> where you control the <font face="Courier New">className</font>, <font face="Courier New">nameSpace</font>, <font face="Courier New">directory</font>, and <font face="Courier New">fileName</font> of the auto-generated code file.&#160; Most of the defaults are fine, but in my case I wanted the generated file to end up in an <font face="Courier New">App_Code</font> directory instead of in the root of the project folder.&#160; If you decide to add in this custom configuration, you need to be aware that you must add the following XML namespace to the <font face="Courier New">configuration</font> root element of your <font face="Courier New">Web.config</font>:</p>  <p><font face="Courier New">xmlns=&quot;http://schemas.microsoft.com/.NetConfiguration/v2.0&quot;</font></p>  <p>Finally, it should be noted that if the website you are building is under source control, you will likely want to always keep this auto-generated code file checked out in order to prevent the file from having its <font face="Courier New">Read-Only</font> attribute set when it's checked in.&#160; If you don't have it checked out, the build will throw out a warning and the generated code file will not be regenerated if changes in your <font face="Courier New">Web.config</font> need to be propagated to it.</p>  <h3>Conclusion</h3>  <p>With all of this in place, you should be able to use the Profile proxy class object in your ASPX code-behind files, just as I gave examples of in my <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/02/aspnet-providers-profile.html">previous post about the ASP.NET Profile system</a>.&#160; Although in my case, I mostly used the static method <font face="Courier New">GetProfile</font> from the auto-generated <font face="Courier New">WebProfile</font><font face="Verdana"> class (the name the Visual Studio Build Task selects by default).</font></p>  <p>As I mentioned when <a title="ASP.NET Providers - Membership, Role, and Profile" href="http://murrayon.net/2009/01/aspnet-providers-membership-role-and.html">I first started the ASP.NET Provider Series of posts</a>, my next blog post will be about some advantages of using this Provider system on IIS 7 and a few issues when your ASP.NET website contains non-ASP.NET content:</p>  <ul>   <li><a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/02/iis-7-and-aspnet-providers-membership.html">IIS 7 and ASP.NET Providers (Membership, Roles, and Profile)</a> </li> </ul> </span>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Martena Gaines</div>
<div class='content'>
Web sites are dynamically compiled and source is distributed with them. Web Applications can be compiled into a single DLL and deployed. You cannot use the app_code folder in WAP projects, but you can with WSP.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ASP.NET Providers - Profile]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/02/09/asp-net-providers-profile/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-09T16:10:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/02/09/asp-net-providers-profile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>This blog post is part of a series about the ASP.NET Providers (namely Membership, Role Management, and Profile). The introductory post in the series can be found at the following link, which introduces the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provider_model">Provider Model pattern</a> and gives a personal example of an implementation I have been working on:</p><ul><li><a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/01/aspnet-providers-membership-role-and.html">ASP.NET Providers - Membership, Role, and Profile</a></li></ul><p>This post will deal with adding Profile properties to your user accounts (and apparently this can also be used with anonymous users as well).&#160; However, I will suggest using a slightly different Profile Provider than what comes in ASP.NET by default.&#160; This will show how easy it is to plug in a different implementation in this very flexible Provider Model.</p> <span class='fullpost'> <h3>SqlProfileProvider vs. SqlTableProfileProvider</h3><p>The <font face="Courier New">SqlProfileProvider</font> is the built-in Profile Provider that ASP.NET comes with by default.&#160; It allows you to define custom fields that make up profiling data you would want to collect and store about your users.&#160; This could be demographics, preferences, or any other useful details.&#160; This specific implementation is designed in a way where no matter what fields you define, your database schema will be compatible with any upgrade Microsoft could send down to patch the Provider system or ASP.NET in general.&#160; The way this is accomplished is by storing a <a title="Binary Large Object" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_large_object">blob</a> of all the field names in one table column and a blob of all the field values in another column; it's similar to the concept of a <a title="Associative Array" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Associative_array">dictionary</a> with key/value pairs.&#160; The difficult part is that these blobs can contain clear-text, XML, and/or binary, depending on how the source data type serializes by default.&#160; Unfortunately, this highly flexible solution is quite unusable if you need a clear view of the Profile data for reporting purposes or stored procedure needs.</p><p>When trying to find an already implemented custom provider that would allow to store each Profile field in its own table column, I came across a <a title="ASP.NET 2.0 SQL Table Profile Provider Released Today" href="http://weblogs.asp.net/scottgu/archive/2006/01/10/435038.aspx">blog post from Scott Guthrie introducing such an implementation done by two Microsoft employees</a>.&#160; The name of this provider is the <font face="Courier New">SqlTableProfileProvider</font>, and it can be found at the following link:</p><p><a href="http://www.asp.net/downloads/sandbox/table-profile-provider-samples/">Table Profile Provider Samples</a></p><p>At the above location, you will find an MSI download that will install a sample project containing a few source code files you can include in your project; you will also find a download link for a &quot;white paper&quot; Word document that explains the usage of the <font face="Courier New">SqlTableProfileProvider</font> and the <font face="Courier New">SqlStoredProcedureProfileProvider</font> custom providers.&#160; The nice thing about both of these providers is that their use in code and their configuration in the Web.config is extremely similar to how the original <font face="Courier New">SqlProfileProvider</font> is used and configured.</p><h3>Setting up the SqlTableProfileProvider</h3><p>As was done with the <a title="ASP.NET Providers - Membership" href="http://murrayon.net/2009/01/aspnet-providers-membership.html">Membership</a> and <a title="ASP.NET Providers - Role Management" href="http://murrayon.net/2009/02/aspnet-providers-role-management.html">Role Management</a> Providers, here is the XML fragment that would go in your <font face="Courier New">Web.config</font>:</p><div style="border-right: gray 1px solid; padding-right: 4px; border-top: gray 1px solid; padding-left: 4px; font-size: 8pt; padding-bottom: 4px; margin: 20px 0px 10px; border-left: gray 1px solid; width: 97.5%; cursor: text; max-height: 325px; line-height: 12pt; padding-top: 4px; border-bottom: gray 1px solid; font-family: consolas, &#39;Courier New&#39;, courier, monospace; background-color: #f4f4f4"><pre style="padding-right: 0px; padding-left: 0px; font-size: 8pt; padding-bottom: 0px; margin: 0em; width: 100%; color: black; border-top-style: none; line-height: 12pt; padding-top: 0px; font-family: consolas, &#39;Courier New&#39;, courier, monospace; border-right-style: none; border-left-style: none; background-color: #f4f4f4; border-bottom-style: none"><span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">configuration</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span>
    <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">connectionStrings</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span>
        <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">add</span> <span style="color: #ff0000">name</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;MyDB&quot;</span> <span style="color: #ff0000">connectionString</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;...&quot;</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">/&gt;</span>
    <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;/</span><span style="color: #800000">connectionStrings</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span>
    <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">system.web</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span>
        ... authentication &amp; authorization settings ...
        <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">profile</span> <span style="color: #ff0000">enabled</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;true&quot;</span>
                 <span style="color: #ff0000">defaultProvider</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;ConfiguredProfileProvider&quot;</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span>
            <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">providers</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span>
                <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">add</span> <span style="color: #ff0000">name</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;ConfiguredProfileProvider&quot;</span>
                     <span style="color: #ff0000">type</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;Microsoft.Samples.SqlTableProfileProvider&quot;</span>
                     <span style="color: #ff0000">connectionStringName</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;MyDB&quot;</span>
                     <span style="color: #ff0000">table</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;custom_Profile&quot;</span>
                     <span style="color: #ff0000">applicationName</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;SampleWebSite&quot;</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">/&gt;</span>
            <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;/</span><span style="color: #800000">providers</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span>
            ... properties section found in the next XML snippet ...
        <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;/</span><span style="color: #800000">profile</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span>
    <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;/</span><span style="color: #800000">system.web</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span>
<span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;/</span><span style="color: #800000">configuration</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span></pre></div><p><strong><u>WARNING</u>: </strong>According to Microsoft, you should <strong><u>never</u></strong> use the default provider settings and should <strong><u>always</u></strong> add a new, configured provider; in addition you <strong><u>must</u></strong> be sure to specify the <font face="Courier New">applicationName</font> attribute! See <a href="http://weblogs.asp.net/scottgu/archive/2006/04/22/Always-set-the-_2200_applicationName_2200_-property-when-configuring-ASP.NET-2.0-Membership-and-other-Providers.aspx">Scott Guthrie's blog post on this topic</a> for more details. Apparently, you can also use a value of <font face="Courier New">&quot;/&quot;</font> for the <font face="Courier New">applicationName</font> and it will use the root application name.</p><p>You'll notice in the <font face="Courier New">type</font> attribute that we are not referencing the default <font face="Courier New">SqlProfileProvider</font> that ships with ASP.NET.&#160; What you need to do is get this new class included or referenced in your solution so that this namespace reference can successfully resolve.&#160; I opted to just include the code files in my solution as is; I chose to place them in my <font face="Courier New">App_Code</font> folder.&#160; The code files you want to grab are likely in the default location that the MSI installed to, which is <font face="Courier New">Program Files/Microsoft/ASP.NET 2.0 Table Profile Provider Samples</font>.&#160; The two files you need are <font face="Courier New">SqlStoredProcedureProfileProvider.cs</font> and <font face="Courier New">SqlTableProfileProvider.cs</font><font face="Verdana">, </font>both of which are found in the <font face="Courier New">App_Code</font> folder of the sample project.&#160; You need to copy both code files to your solution, as it appears that the <font face="Courier New">SqlTableProfileProvider</font> depends on some logic in the <font face="Courier New">SqlStoredProcedureProfileProvider</font> for some reason.</p><p>Also note the <font face="Courier New">table</font> attribute above (which is not present in the built-in <font face="Courier New">SqlProfileProvider</font>), which tells the provider which table in your database will be storing the custom Profile fields.&#160; As for the &quot;properties section&quot; referenced near the end of the above snippet, this is where you specify the custom Profile fields and their mappings to column names in the specified database table.&#160; The advantage of specifying this information in the <font face="Courier New">Web.config</font> is that you will be able to get programmatic access to these fields as strongly-typed properties on a proxy class named <font face="Courier New">Profile</font> in your code-behind.&#160; Here is a sample <font face="Courier New">properties</font> configuration:</p><div style="border-right: gray 1px solid; padding-right: 4px; border-top: gray 1px solid; padding-left: 4px; font-size: 8pt; padding-bottom: 4px; margin: 20px 0px 10px; border-left: gray 1px solid; width: 97.5%; cursor: text; max-height: 300px; line-height: 12pt; padding-top: 4px; border-bottom: gray 1px solid; font-family: consolas, &#39;Courier New&#39;, courier, monospace; background-color: #f4f4f4"><pre style="padding-right: 0px; padding-left: 0px; font-size: 8pt; padding-bottom: 0px; margin: 0em; width: 100%; color: black; border-top-style: none; line-height: 12pt; padding-top: 0px; font-family: consolas, &#39;Courier New&#39;, courier, monospace; border-right-style: none; border-left-style: none; background-color: #f4f4f4; border-bottom-style: none"><span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">properties</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span>
    <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">add</span> <span style="color: #ff0000">name</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;FirstName&quot;</span>
         <span style="color: #ff0000">type</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;string&quot;</span>
         <span style="color: #ff0000">defaultValue</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;[null]&quot;</span>
         <span style="color: #ff0000">customProviderData</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;FirstName;nvarchar&quot;</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">/&gt;</span>
    <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">add</span> <span style="color: #ff0000">name</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;Age&quot;</span>
         <span style="color: #ff0000">type</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;int&quot;</span>
         <span style="color: #ff0000">customProviderData</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;Age;int&quot;</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">/&gt;</span>
    <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">add</span> <span style="color: #ff0000">name</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;AccountExpiration&quot;</span>
         <span style="color: #ff0000">type</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;DateTime&quot;</span>
         <span style="color: #ff0000">defaultValue</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;[null]&quot;</span>
         <span style="color: #ff0000">customProviderData</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;AccountExpiration;datetime&quot;</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">/&gt;</span>
    <span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;</span><span style="color: #800000">add</span> <span style="color: #ff0000">name</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;CookieID&quot;</span>
         <span style="color: #ff0000">type</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;System.Guid&quot;</span>
         <span style="color: #ff0000">defaultValue</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;[null]&quot;</span>
         <span style="color: #ff0000">customProviderData</span><span style="color: #0000ff">=&quot;CookieID;uniqueidentifier&quot;</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">/&gt;</span>
<span style="color: #0000ff">&lt;/</span><span style="color: #800000">properties</span><span style="color: #0000ff">&gt;</span></pre></div><p>The Profile system provides a configuration point for each Profile field called <font face="Courier New">customProviderData</font>.&#160; It appears the default <font face="Courier New">SqlProfileProvider</font> doesn't even look at this additional attribute, but rather reserves this configuration point for use by custom implemented Profile providers.&#160; The <font face="Courier New">SqlTableProfileProvider </font>utilizes this extra metadata field as a place to put mapping information for a column name and ADO.NET database type.&#160; If you have questions about which ADO.NET and .NET types to use/specify in this configuration, there is helpful information in the accompanying white paper found on the download site.&#160; Also found in that document is a great discussion you may want to read about the <font face="Courier New">defaultValue</font> attribute, what it configures, and how it might differ for value types (such as <font face="Courier New">integer</font>).</p><h3>Creating the Database Table</h3><p>Now that you have the code files in your solution and have configured the Profile fields, you need to create the custom table in the database that this provider will query and update.&#160; Here is a sample SQL definition for our custom profile table:</p><div style="border-right: gray 1px solid; padding-right: 4px; border-top: gray 1px solid; padding-left: 4px; font-size: 8pt; padding-bottom: 4px; margin: 20px 0px 10px; border-left: gray 1px solid; width: 97.5%; cursor: text; max-height: 200px; line-height: 12pt; padding-top: 4px; border-bottom: gray 1px solid; font-family: consolas, &#39;Courier New&#39;, courier, monospace; background-color: #f4f4f4"><pre style="padding-right: 0px; padding-left: 0px; font-size: 8pt; padding-bottom: 0px; margin: 0em; width: 100%; color: black; border-top-style: none; line-height: 12pt; padding-top: 0px; font-family: consolas, &#39;Courier New&#39;, courier, monospace; border-right-style: none; border-left-style: none; background-color: #f4f4f4; border-bottom-style: none"><span style="color: #0000ff">create</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">table</span> dbo.custom_Profile
(
    UserId               uniqueidentifier <span style="color: #0000ff">not</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">null</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">Primary</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">Key</span>,
    FirstName            nvarchar(50) <span style="color: #0000ff">null</span>,
    Age                  <span style="color: #0000ff">int</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">null</span>,
    AccountExpiration    datetime <span style="color: #0000ff">null</span>,
    CookieID             uniqueidentifier <span style="color: #0000ff">null</span>,
    LastUpdatedDate      datetime <span style="color: #0000ff">not</span> <span style="color: #0000ff">null</span>
)
go</pre></div><p>Note that the <font face="Courier New">SqlTableProfileProvider</font> requires two extra columns in addition to your custom defined Profile properties, namely <font face="Courier New">UserId</font> and <font face="Courier New">LastUpdatedDate</font>.&#160; One other thing to be aware of is that if you use the Membership API to delete a user programmatically, this will remove all entries related to that user in the database <strong><u>except</u></strong> from your custom Profile table.&#160; I believe this might be because the Profile system can apparently be used independently of the Membership system, even allowing you to store Profile data on anonymous, unauthenticated users.&#160; I think the same caution would go for any utility that presumably uses this Membership API under the covers, such as the <font face="Courier New">ASP.NET Website Administration Tool</font> launched from Visual Studio that I referred to earlier in this series with a post titled <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/01/aspnet-providers-getting-started.html">ASP.NET Providers - Getting Started</a>.&#160; Up to this point, I have resorted to manually clearing out Profile table rows myself that are linked to the membership account being removed from the database.</p><p>Also, if your web site is using a Windows user or system account for the identity of the worker process, you'll want to make sure that set of credentials has <font face="Courier New">SELECT</font>, <font face="Courier New">INSERT</font>, <font face="Courier New">UPDATE</font>, and <font face="Courier New">DELETE</font> permissions granted to it for this new custom database table you created.&#160; There are also some <font face="Courier New">EXECUTE</font>, <font face="Courier New">SELECT</font>, and <font face="Courier New">UPDATE</font> permissions required on a few of the already-existing stored procedures that the Provider system uses.&#160; Again, check the accompanying white paper on the download site for a discussion about these procedure and for some SQL statements to help you automate the granting of these permissions.</p><h3>The Profile Proxy Class</h3><p>If you are using the <font face="Courier New">Web Site</font> project template in Visual Studio, then you are good to go with using the <font face="Courier New">Profile</font> proxy class that can be used anywhere in your code to retrieve and update Profile fields on the current user.&#160; The availability of this <font face="Courier New">Profile</font> class is independent of whether you are using the built-in ASP.NET <font face="Courier New">SqlProfileProvider</font> or the custom <font face="Courier New">SqlTableProfileProvider</font> that I've been showcasing thus far.&#160; However, if you are using the <font face="Courier New">Web Application</font> project template, this proxy object is not auto-generated for you by Visual Studio.&#160; For a detailed discussion of the problem and a working solution, see my next post which is entitled <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/02/aspnet-profile-and-web-application.html">ASP.NET Profile and Web Application Projects</a>.</p><p>Use of this <font face="Courier New">Profile</font> class couldn't be easier and is exactly as you would expect it to be.&#160; Here is a code snippet that both retrieves and updates strongly-typed Profile properties (exactly as they were defined in the <font face="Courier New">Web.config</font>) using this proxy object:</p><div style="border-right: gray 1px solid; padding-right: 4px; border-top: gray 1px solid; padding-left: 4px; font-size: 8pt; padding-bottom: 4px; margin: 20px 0px 10px; border-left: gray 1px solid; width: 97.5%; cursor: text; max-height: 200px; line-height: 12pt; padding-top: 4px; border-bottom: gray 1px solid; font-family: consolas, &#39;Courier New&#39;, courier, monospace; background-color: #f4f4f4"><pre style="padding-right: 0px; padding-left: 0px; font-size: 8pt; padding-bottom: 0px; margin: 0em; width: 100%; color: black; border-top-style: none; line-height: 12pt; padding-top: 0px; font-family: consolas, &#39;Courier New&#39;, courier, monospace; border-right-style: none; border-left-style: none; background-color: #f4f4f4; border-bottom-style: none"><span style="color: #008000">// Set Profile property</span>
Profile.FirstName = txtBoxFirstName.Text;

<span style="color: #008000">// Retrieve Profile property</span>
<span style="color: #0000ff">int</span> age = Profile.Age;</pre></div><h3>Read On!</h3><p>This crash course of the ASP.NET Provider system is pretty much done I guess you could say, as far as a tutorial goes that is.&#160; I still have another two posts on the radar that will be coming over the next few days regarding issues and workarounds that I encountered.&#160; One post will deal with generating this <font face="Courier New">Profile</font> proxy class under the Visual Studio <font face="Courier New">Web Application</font> project template.&#160; The other post will be about the advantages of using this system under IIS 7 found in Windows Vista and Server 2008; it will also include some issues with using this system if some of your content is static HTML instead of ASPX pages.&#160; Here are the links to these two posts:</p><ul><li><a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/02/aspnet-profile-and-web-application.html">ASP.NET Profile and Web Application Projects</a> </li><li><a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/02/iis-7-and-aspnet-providers-membership.html">IIS 7 and ASP.NET Providers (Membership, Roles, and Profile)</a> </li></ul><p>It has been a very pleasant experience overall to work with the ASP.NET Provider system because of it's highly customizable and flexible design.&#160; If your <a title="ASP.NET Providers - Membership" href="http://murrayon.net/2009/01/aspnet-providers-membership.html">Membership</a>, <a title="ASP.NET Providers - Role Management" href="http://murrayon.net/2009/02/aspnet-providers-role-management.html">Role Management</a>, and Profile needs are fairly common and typical, this framework is a piece of cake to incorporate into your product (including your existing ones, no matter how out-of-date they are).&#160; Hope you've enjoyed the series!</p>
</span>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>mamali</div>
<div class='content'>
perfect, thank you very much...</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Bryan</div>
<div class='content'>
I&#39;ve been using the profile system with good results, but in the last couple of weeks, I must have made some change because now I&#39;m getting the error: &quot;Column name &#39;UserID&#39; appears more than once in the result column list.&quot; I can see the SQL command that&#39;s generated in SqlTableProfileProvider.vb, and it indeed contains two columns with name UserID. The problem is, I&#39;m unable to find the source of the second UserID column. What can I do to trace and resolve the problem?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Esteban Araya</div>
<div class='content'>
@Shalan &amp; Mike:<br /><br />I&#39;d just store the photo on a file server, and then just store a UNC path to the photo on the custom profile table.<br /><br />That way, all you&#39;d have to do is: read the path, load the photo &amp; display it.<br /><br />Hope this helps!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mike Murray</div>
<div class='content'>
Ya know, I&#39;m not really sure.  But I am wondering if I&#39;ve got something that might lead to an answer.  I&#39;m looking at the examples in my blog post and notice the Guid field.  In order for that data type to work, it had to be specified as System.Guid, I&#39;m assuming because it&#39;s not a primitive type.  Perhaps something similar has to be done, like System.Array or System.Array&lt;Byte&gt;...not really sure.  The other thing I can think of is maybe using the primitive version of &quot;byte&quot; instead of &quot;Byte&quot;.<br /><br />Just a few random guesses.  Let us know if you find the resolution and post back here.  Thanks!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>shalan</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi Mike.  Excellent article! I've been using TableProvider for some time now, but recently I had a first case where the user wanted to incorporated photos as part of their profile.<br /><br />I have tried to accomplish but to no avail. Its setup as a varbinary field in the database, and a Byte[] datatype in the web.config, but I keep getting an error saying that it could not load type "Byte[]".  Have you tried this?  Do you have any suggestions?<br /><br />Thanx!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mike Murray</div>
<div class='content'>
Very good question.<BR/><BR/>In my particular use case, the need to delete a user account from the system would be so rare that I am content to leave it a manual process.  And since I'll be the one managing it for a while, I'm content with this solution for the time being.<BR/><BR/>I will give this question some thought, however, and I will post back if come up with an idea or two...that is if someone else doesn't beat me to it here in the comments.<BR/><BR/>Please do let us know if you come up with something yourself.  Thanks, and good luck.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Has anybody came up with a way to automatically delete custom profile table along with the rest of the membership information?</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
