<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: MSBuild | Mike Murray]]></title>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/categories/msbuild/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-17T19:32:47-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://mkmurray.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Murray]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Custom Setup Bootstrappers]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/11/11/custom-setup-bootstrappers/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-11T15:03:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/11/11/custom-setup-bootstrappers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>At work, we have a line of desktop products for one of clients installed on the user’s Windows machine via MSI installers.&#160; We use Visual Studio Setup Projects to create the MSI installers.&#160; Visual Studio also provides the ability to create setup bootstrappers to make sure the user has all the prerequisites needed for the MSI install technology and any dependencies required by your desktop product.&#160; These bootstrappers are unmanaged code, because you can’t always depend on the .NET framework already being there (at least not until everyone is off of XP and lower).&#160; I have developed a solution that has worked for the last year or more, but has felt clumsy and slapped together.&#160; Recently I found the <a href="http://dotnetinstaller.codeplex.com/">open source project called dotNetInstaller</a> which has better provided me with the control and flexibility I need for custom logic during bootstrap and install time.&#160; I’ll first introduce you to my “hack” solution.</p> <span class="fullpost">   <p>It has been difficult for me to find ways to tie into the bootstrapper logic workflow to add in custom logic during installs, and Visual Studio is very rigid in its flexibility and basic in its configuration options in this regard.&#160; Until recently, I had settled on writing managed, C# code for this custom logic meant to run before or after the MSI installer, and then creating another unmanaged <font face="Courier New">setup.exe</font> bootstrapper to ensure the .NET framework was installed just so that executable could run.&#160; So the user would run this new unmanaged <font face="Courier New">setup.exe</font> bootstrapper (making sure .NET framework was installed), which would then call my managed custom logic executable, which would then call the MSI installer’s unmanaged, Visual Studio-generated <font face="Courier New">setup.exe</font> bootstrapper (ensuring more prerequisites were installed), which would then finally install the MSI, and which would then lastly return to my managed custom logic executable for any post-install, clean up logic.&#160; I describe this solution in full (and how to generate the same bootstrappers that Visual Studio creates using MSBuild outside the IDE) in a StackOverflow.com answer that I submitted:</p>    <p><a title="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1106768/how-can-i-reverse-engineer-an-installer-that-was-written-with-ghost-installer/1121846#1121846" href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1106768/how-can-i-reverse-engineer-an-installer-that-was-written-with-ghost-installer/1121846#1121846">http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1106768/how-can-i-reverse-engineer-an-installer-that-was-written-with-ghost-installer/1121846#1121846</a></p>    <p>Well, recently I found the <a href="http://dotnetinstaller.codeplex.com/">dotNetInstaller project on CodePlex.com</a> and have found it to be the control and flexibility I need for custom logic when bootstrapping installers.&#160; Not only does it give you great control over prerequisite install order, it also gives you the ability to run code after MSI install and to also filter on CPU architecture types, OS versions, and other registry or file system conditions.&#160; I have currently setup branching scenarios for the prerequisites based on if the user has a 32-bit (x86) or 64-bit (x64) OS.&#160; This utility will even let you brand the bootstrapper with a banner and icon, which is a change of pace from the plain and unlabeled bootstrapper that Visual Studio and MSBuild produce.</p>    <p>If you have custom bootstrapping needs, I have to highly recommend you give dotNetInstaller a look.&#160; Hopefully it will prove as flexible and powerful for your needs as it has for mine.</p> </span>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ASP.NET Profile and Web Application Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/02/11/asp-net-profile-and-web-application-projects/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-11T15:08:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/02/11/asp-net-profile-and-web-application-projects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I talked at length about the ASP.NET <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provider_model">Provider Model pattern</a> and the ease of implementing several built-in services you can have for free with ASP.NET 2.0 in <a title="ASP.NET Providers - Membership, Role, and Profile" href="http://murrayon.net/2009/01/aspnet-providers-membership-role-and.html">my previous series of posts</a>.&#160; In this post, I will be discussing a few issues I ran into using the Profile system with the <font face="Courier New">Web Application</font> project template instead of the <font face="Courier New">Web Site</font> project template as found in Visual Studio's list of default project templates.</p>  <p>The crux of the issue is that Visual Studio doesn't automatically generate the <font face="Courier New">Profile</font> proxy class object when using the <font face="Courier New">Web Application</font> project template, like it does with the <font face="Courier New">Web Site</font> project template.&#160; This proxy class can be used to obtain access to strongly-typed properties representing the custom Profile fields you specified in your <font face="Courier New">Web.config</font>.&#160; This is a very convenient way to access a user's Profile data, both for authenticated and for anonymous users.</p>  <p>Let's discuss the issue a little further and then I will present a workaround that I found and have successfully implemented in my own project.</p> <span class='fullpost'> <h3>VS Project Templates:&#160; Web Site vs. Web Application</h3>  <p>It appears that Microsoft has tried to differentiate these two project templates as much as possible in Visual Studio 2008.&#160; In 2005, you would go to the <font face="Courier New">New Project</font> dialog window and you would see these two <font face="Courier New">Web</font> project templates side-by-side, wondering what difference it would make if you chose one over the other.&#160; However, in Visual Studio 2008, it appears they reworked this whole dialog and menu system for starting a new project so that you would never see these two project templates side-by-side.&#160; In 2008, you have more than one option in the <font face="Courier New">File</font> menu for starting a project; those options are <font face="Courier New">File | New | Project</font> and <font face="Courier New">File | New | Web Site</font>.&#160; The first option is the one that will get you to the <font face="Courier New">ASP.NET Web Application</font> template, while the second takes you to the <font face="Courier New">ASP.NET Web Site</font> project template.</p>  <p>Now as for the differences between these two templates, I'll outline a few of the main differences and give a little bit of history of how these two templates came to coexist.&#160; The history in a nutshell is that Visual Studio 2005 came out with the <font face="Courier New">Web Site</font> project template to replace the old, but proven project configuration used by ASP.NET 1.x.&#160; In the opinion of many, the old template better encouraged Object-Oriented design practices.&#160; The new template had no project file for explicitly delineating what files where included in the project and namespacing was quite cumbersome, as the only painless design was to let everything pile up into one big default namespace.&#160; A few other changes involved taking ASP.NET back to compiling on the fly at the web server and also drastically changing the organization of UI template and code-behind files.&#160; It appears the intention was to closely mimic the configuration and deployment practices of popular agile languages like PHP and Ruby on Rails.</p>  <p>In the Service Pack 1 of Visual Studio 2005, Microsoft decided to resurrect the older project template under the name of <font face="Courier New">Web Application</font>.&#160; There is evidence to suggest that Microsoft considers this latter project template an &quot;enterprise&quot; project type, as compared to the casual <font face="Courier New">Web Site</font> project template.&#160; With the advent of Visual Studio 2008, it is apparent that Microsoft is committed to supporting both project types for at least a little while.&#160; For a more detailed discussion of the history and differences of these two project templates, I suggest the following blog post by <a href="http://reddnet.net/code/">Stephen M. Redd</a>:</p>  <ul>   <li><a href="http://reddnet.net/code/aspnet-web-site-vs-web-application/">ASP.NET - Web Site vs. Web Application</a></li> </ul>  <h3>Web Profile Builder by Joe Wrobel</h3>  <p>The ability to retrieve and update your custom Profile fields at design time via strongly-typed properties on the <font face="Courier New">Profile</font> proxy class is extremely convenient.&#160; Unfortunately, you get no such compiler and intellisense love if you are using the <font face="Courier New">Web Application</font> project template for your site.</p>  <p>In trying to find a workaround, I came across a <a title="Web Profile Builder for Web Application Projects" href="http://weblogs.asp.net/joewrobel/archive/2008/02/03/web-profile-builder-for-web-application-projects.aspx">blog post by Joe Wrobel introducing a project he worked on to solve this issue</a>.&#160; It's called the <font face="Courier New">Web Profile Builder</font> (here's a <a title="Web Profile Builder" href="http://code.msdn.microsoft.com/WebProfileBuilder/Release/ProjectReleases.aspx">link to it's project page on MSDN Code Gallery</a>) and it was based on a project called the <a href="http://www.codeplex.com/WebProfile">Web Profile Generator</a>, which was a Visual Studio 2005 Add-In project found on <a href="http://www.codeplex.com/">CodePlex</a>.&#160; The latter project seems to have not been worked on in over a year and a half, nor does it seem to be compatible with Visual Studio 2008.&#160; Hence, Joe feeling the need to start up on his own project, with a few improvements on the side of course.</p>  <p>In Joe's introductory post to the project, he mentions he changed the Visual Studio integration from being a plug-in to being an MSBuild Build Task.&#160; The method for incorporating the Build Task into your project is to add a line into your project file (the one with file extension <font face="Courier New">.csproj</font>).&#160; In case you weren't aware, Visual Studio project files are just <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MSBuild">MSBuild</a> build scripts.&#160; For details about where to put this line in the file (and about a message Visual Studio pops up when it detects you've mucked with the project file), be sure to check out <a title="Web Profile Builder for Web Application Projects" href="http://weblogs.asp.net/joewrobel/archive/2008/02/03/web-profile-builder-for-web-application-projects.aspx">Joe's post on the Web Profile Builder project</a>.</p>  <p>There are a couple of other things I need to point out about using the Build Task that weren't entirely clear to me beforehand.&#160; The build task actually generates a C# code file that is intended to be included into your project; once it's generated, you need to go to the <font face="Courier New">Solution Explorer</font> and explicitly add it as a file in your project (one way is through the <font face="Courier New">Add | Existing Item</font> menu option).&#160; One of the main things that helped me decide to use this solution and how to configure it was reading two blog posts from <a href="http://www.codersbarn.com/">Anthony Grace</a>; the second post below has a great excerpt apparently from the <font face="Courier New">Web Profile Builder</font> documentation that explains the process I outlined above in a bit more detail:</p>  <ul>   <li><a href="http://www.codersbarn.com/post/2008/06/ASPNET-Web-Site-versus-Web-Application-Project.aspx">ASP.NET: Web Site versus Web Application Project</a></li>    <li><a href="http://www.codersbarn.com/post/2008/07/10/ASPNET-PayPal-Subscriptions-IPN.aspx">ASP.NET PayPal Subscription IPN</a></li> </ul>  <p>Also, it is not necessary to do the steps in the <font face="Courier New">Extended Usage</font> section of Joe's blog post.&#160; They are optional configuration points in the <font face="Courier New">Web.config</font> where you control the <font face="Courier New">className</font>, <font face="Courier New">nameSpace</font>, <font face="Courier New">directory</font>, and <font face="Courier New">fileName</font> of the auto-generated code file.&#160; Most of the defaults are fine, but in my case I wanted the generated file to end up in an <font face="Courier New">App_Code</font> directory instead of in the root of the project folder.&#160; If you decide to add in this custom configuration, you need to be aware that you must add the following XML namespace to the <font face="Courier New">configuration</font> root element of your <font face="Courier New">Web.config</font>:</p>  <p><font face="Courier New">xmlns=&quot;http://schemas.microsoft.com/.NetConfiguration/v2.0&quot;</font></p>  <p>Finally, it should be noted that if the website you are building is under source control, you will likely want to always keep this auto-generated code file checked out in order to prevent the file from having its <font face="Courier New">Read-Only</font> attribute set when it's checked in.&#160; If you don't have it checked out, the build will throw out a warning and the generated code file will not be regenerated if changes in your <font face="Courier New">Web.config</font> need to be propagated to it.</p>  <h3>Conclusion</h3>  <p>With all of this in place, you should be able to use the Profile proxy class object in your ASPX code-behind files, just as I gave examples of in my <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/02/aspnet-providers-profile.html">previous post about the ASP.NET Profile system</a>.&#160; Although in my case, I mostly used the static method <font face="Courier New">GetProfile</font> from the auto-generated <font face="Courier New">WebProfile</font><font face="Verdana"> class (the name the Visual Studio Build Task selects by default).</font></p>  <p>As I mentioned when <a title="ASP.NET Providers - Membership, Role, and Profile" href="http://murrayon.net/2009/01/aspnet-providers-membership-role-and.html">I first started the ASP.NET Provider Series of posts</a>, my next blog post will be about some advantages of using this Provider system on IIS 7 and a few issues when your ASP.NET website contains non-ASP.NET content:</p>  <ul>   <li><a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/02/iis-7-and-aspnet-providers-membership.html">IIS 7 and ASP.NET Providers (Membership, Roles, and Profile)</a> </li> </ul> </span>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Martena Gaines</div>
<div class='content'>
Web sites are dynamically compiled and source is distributed with them. Web Applications can be compiled into a single DLL and deployed. You cannot use the app_code folder in WAP projects, but you can with WSP.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Visual Studio Web Deployment Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2008/02/28/visual-studio-web-deployment-projects/"/>
    <updated>2008-02-28T09:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2008/02/28/visual-studio-web-deployment-projects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>So nearly a year and a half ago, a Microsoft team released a Visual Studio 2005 add-on that would add the &quot;<font face="Courier New">Web Deployment</font>&quot; project type to your IDE.&#160; A few of the advantages of this new project type are:</p>  <ul>   <li>More control over the number of assemblies generated by a pre-compiled web project, as well as control over their naming. </li>    <li>The ability to utilize the full power of MSBuild to customize your build process, including support for opening and editing the web deployment MSBuild project file directly in the IDE (with full intellisense support). </li>    <li>The ability to define and use custom build-configurations inside Visual Studio, and define per-build configuration options (for example, you could define custom build configurations like “staging” in addition to the standard &quot;debug&quot; and &quot;release&quot;). </li>    <li>The ability to customize and modify a web application’s web.config file at deployment according to build configuration (&quot;debug&quot;, &quot;staging&quot;, &quot;release&quot;, etc.). </li> </ul> <span class='fullpost'> <p>Here is a link that discusses it further and gives a screenshot walkthrough of it:&#160; <a title="http://weblogs.asp.net/scottgu/archive/2005/11/06/429723.aspx" href="http://weblogs.asp.net/scottgu/archive/2005/11/06/429723.aspx">http://weblogs.asp.net/scottgu/archive/2005/11/06/429723.aspx</a></p>  <p>Well, now that same team has included an enhanced version for VS 2008.&#160; Here is a link discussing the improvements and additions:&#160; <a title="http://weblogs.asp.net/scottgu/archive/2008/01/28/vs-2008-web-deployment-project-support-released.aspx" href="http://weblogs.asp.net/scottgu/archive/2008/01/28/vs-2008-web-deployment-project-support-released.aspx">http://weblogs.asp.net/scottgu/archive/2008/01/28/vs-2008-web-deployment-project-support-released.aspx</a></p>  <p>Also, the IIS team at Microsoft has a new command-line utility called MSDeploy that helps with deploying and syncing web projects across all of the servers in your server farm:&#160; <a title="http://blogs.iis.net/msdeploy/archive/2008/01/22/welcome-to-the-web-deployment-team-blog.aspx" href="http://blogs.iis.net/msdeploy/archive/2008/01/22/welcome-to-the-web-deployment-team-blog.aspx">http://blogs.iis.net/msdeploy/archive/2008/01/22/welcome-to-the-web-deployment-team-blog.aspx</a></p>  <p>Sounds like fun to me.</p> </span>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
