<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: SOLID | Mike Murray]]></title>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/categories/solid/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-03T23:33:20-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mkmurray.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Murray]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Develop with Passion bootcamp course - Denver 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/05/31/develop-with-passion-bootcamp-course-denver-2011/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-31T09:27:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/05/31/develop-with-passion-bootcamp-course-denver-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p><a href="http://paceyourself.net/" target="_blank">A very talented coworker</a> and I recently went to JP Boodhoo’s <a href="http://www.jpboodhoo.com/training.oo" target="_blank">Develop with Passion bootcamp training course</a> (previously known as Nothin but .NET). I had originally heard of the course from <a href="http://www.davesquared.net/" target="_blank">Dave Tchepak</a> who <a href="http://www.davesquared.net/2009/08/nothin-but-net-sydney-2009-day-1.html" target="_blank">attended the course nearly two years ago</a>. This blog post is a wrap-up of my thoughts and feelings about the course itself, <a href="http://www.jpboodhoo.com/" target="_blank">JP Boodhoo</a> as the instructor &amp; experienced craftsman, and the .NET development community in general.</p> <span class="fullpost">   <p>My prior impressions of the course from what I had read was that I would be in awe of JP's coding and design skills and very overwhelmed with the feeling that I didn't really know how to code; also that I would get no sleep at all that week, going from early morning to past midnight every day. I had also heard from a previous course member (off the record) that JP’s organization and direction with course material was a bit disorganized back then (luckily this has changed significantly since he had taken the course). I was really excited to see some good BDD in action, get my TDD passion ignited again (I had actually mentioned on twitter recently that my motivation for test was waning as of late), and see JP's mad Vim skills (since I have gotten into that the last few months).</p>    <p>Overall, I was pleasantly surprised with the fulfillment of most of my positive expectations and initial impressions going into the course. JP's personality and passion are infectious, and his teaching skills are pretty top-notch. The course material was well-structured and there was a clear direction for what we hoped to cover throughout the week (and yet, he was still flexible enough to be able to briefly entertain an off-topic direction the students wanted to take the course). He stayed true to the advertised 9am-9pm every day no matter what. He said that when he did the late nighters with previous courses, people came back the next day with little sleep and trashed as far as coding &amp; learning capabilities go.</p>    <p>Watching him code so efficiently is quite a treat. He automates anything he does more than once so that a particular task doesn’t ever get in his way and hold him back the next time. His <a href="http://www.autohotkey.com/" target="_blank">AutoHotkey</a> scripts and automation tools that he has put together are absolutely incredible. He briefly touched the mouse two times the entire week, and it only for when one of his programs or Windows VM was wigging out. Screens and dialogs flew by so fast, you could tell he wasn't going to let any UI (even Visual Studio) get in the way of his productivity to code. He mentioned he will be open sourcing some of his scripts that he uses to keep his development environment consistent across OS platforms. Definitely cool stuff.</p>    <p>As far as JP's actual coding/design skills, I am absolutely floored. He certainly understands C# and .NET well. But it's his Object-Oriented design skills that blew us away. I've realized I don't really know OO design. I think too mechanically about the implementation of the solution instead of focusing on breaking down the problem into smaller manageable chunks. His TDD skills (both Top Down Design and Test Driven Development) are amazing. I've never been a fan of the TDD samples and intros I've seen (where the instructors do the absolute dumbest thing to make the test pass; JP admitted that style didn’t jive with him either). I've always thought that Behavior Driven Development and Top-Down Design were the way to go if I were to have tests drive my designs (or have tests at all for that matter; I'm still having trouble finding enthusiasm for tests written after development for modules and units). So it was great to see a master at that particular craft. It made me excited to use tests as a tool to guide my OO design, behavior discovery, and problem solving.</p>    <p>Some of you may recall that I had <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/11/anagram-code-kata-bdd-mspec.html" target="_blank">previously investigated BDD, Machine.Specifications, and Top-Down Design a year and a half ago doing the Anagram Code Kata</a>. I think I can recognize better design and responsibility break-up and assignment nowadays. I likely will blog on these subjects again this year with new &amp; improved passion and knowledge.</p>    <p>There was one sad takeaway for me personally from the course, which was a sense of disappointment in the .NET development community in general. Giving myself some time since the course to really think it through, I’m realizing I’m probably being too tough on our community, as I know each Dev community out there suffers from it’s own set of problems. But I don’t want to excuse our shortcomings either; rather, I would like to point them out so that we can focus on them and root those weaknesses out. I think our community in specific is unique in that there is a big shot company that dictates the direction our community should take, sometimes taking credit for all the innovation. Things are improving lately no doubt; it appears Microsoft is listening more and more and trying to let outsiders get involved and contribute.</p>    <p>But we as .NET devs need to step up and take matters into our own hands, we need to take better control of the code we write and encourage best practices within the realms of our responsibilities and influence. I believe many .NET shops rely on the tools sent down from above so heavily that we don’t really solve problems anymore. JP’s focus on problem solving and code katas from the course attack this deficiency at its core. I do somewhat blame our university Computer Science programs for not teaching real OO (a great discussion on formalism versus hermeneutics in a book I highly recommend, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Object-Thinking-DV-Microsoft-Professional-David/dp/0735619654" target="_blank">Object Thinking</a>), but at some point we have to take what we were given and no matter our current standing, focus on sharpening our skills through practice and continuous learning. It boils down to individual responsibility for our current skill set and progression as a software craftsman. JP’s course does a terrific job of waking you up to that realization and inspiring you to be a better professional at your craft.</p>    <p>I have a few takeaways from the course that I’ll publicly spell out now. First, I (and hopefully our whole team) need to better understand design patterns and have them become integral to our code discussions. JP was all about efficiency in keystrokes and related dev tasks, and it seems natural that our language and code discussions could benefit from more efficient communication using design pattern terminology to convey a lot about a specific design concept in only a few words. Second, I hope that I (and our team again) can really put our tests to work for us, helping us recognize the problem to be solved or the behavior that needs to be captured, and then guiding us toward a simple solution. The third takeaway is related to that last part, and that is to have simple solutions that are distributed across simple object implementations (focusing on behaviors) that adhere to SOLID principles. It appears the key is to not focus on implementation specifics until the very last responsible moment; if done right, the implementations to create should be so clear cut and trivial, almost spelled right out in the tests themselves. It’s hard to put into words, but it seems crucial to focus first on the collaborators needed while designing code at the higher levels, finding ways to offload as much responsibility as possible (at least that’s what it felt like) onto dependencies that have yet to be designed and implemented. Designing Top-Down in this way gave such simple and elegant solutions that were totally extensible and adhered to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open/closed_principle" target="_blank">Open/Closed Principle</a> better than any other code I have ever seen before. Perhaps as I blog more about this, I’ll be able to better put this style of coding into words (especially as I try to better understand it myself; it all seems so magical still!).</p>    <p>Overall, a great course that I highly recommend to all. JP has mentioned doing a similar course in Ruby, which I personally find especially interesting, given the same design/coding techniques would seem to run against a lot less friction compared to the heavy reliance on interfaces and mocking that C# require.</p>    <p>Stay tuned as I try to put some of this stuff into practice!</p> </span>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[F# Pipeline Operator in C#?]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/09/06/f-pipeline-operator-in-c/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-06T20:22:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/09/06/f-pipeline-operator-in-c</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I am currently reading the <a href="http://www.manning.com/petricek/" target="_blank">Real-World Functional Programming</a> book from <a href="http://www.manning.com/" target="_blank">Manning Publications</a>. It’s mostly an exercise in learning F#, but also to improve my C# code as well. I finally learned what the F# pipelining operator (<font face="Courier New">|&gt;</font>) is all about, and I was so impressed I thought I would try to figure out how to bring it into C# if possible.</p> <span class="fullpost">   <h3>Introducing the F# Pipeline Operator</h3>    <p>Here is some F# code that defines a list of integers and a pair of functions.&#160; They are then used in a few “higher-order” functions (functions that utilize other functions as parameters or return values, according to my book).&#160; <font face="courier new">List.filter</font> is equivalent to the LINQ <font face="Courier New">IEnumerable.Where()</font> extension method, and <font face="Courier New">List.map</font> is equivalent to <font face="Courier New">IEnumerable.Select()</font>.</p>    <pre class="brush: csharp">let numbers = [ 1 .. 10 ]
let isOdd(n) = n % 2 = 1
let square(n) = n * n

List.filter isOdd numbers
List.map square (List.filter isOdd numbers)</pre>

  <p>The interesting part is the last line of code, where it is argued that you lose a little bit of code readability because the function that is actually executed first (<font face="Courier New">List.filter</font>) is found second in the expression statement.&#160; Enter the F# pipelining operator:</p>

  <pre class="brush: csharp">let squared =
  numbers
  |&gt; List.filter isOdd
  |&gt; List.map square</pre>

  <p>Even though we’re no longer a compact, one-liner expression, I think we’ve gained some code readability.&#160; It says to take the list <font face="Courier New">numbers</font> and perform the following manipulations in the exact order listed.&#160; Cool stuff, if I say so myself.</p>

  <h3>“There is No Charge for Awesomeness…or Attractiveness”</h3>

  <p>(Sorry, I’ve been watching the movie <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0441773/" target="_blank">Kung Fu Panda</a> a lot with my kids lately.&#160; Funny stuff.)&#160; So can this awesomeness be brought over into C#?&#160; I opened up Visual Studio and tried to see if I could figure out how to define my own operator or reuse one of the existing ones.</p>

  <p>I realize C# is a pretty tough language to flip keywords and operators around and invent new syntax with (ok, it’s impossible), but I tried anyway.&#160; The type of code readability issue I wanted to remedy is the same as with the F# code snippet above.&#160; I thought it would be nice to make C# code like the following statement more readable and digestible (especially the execution order):</p>

  <pre class="brush: csharp">Convert.ToInt32(Context.Request[“requestParam”].Trim());</pre>

  <p>As I started to (unsuccessfully) beat out some pretty rough code, I ran into problems with trying to make extension methods that are operator definition overloads and errors saying “<font face="Courier New">One of the parameters of a binary operator must be the containing type.</font>”&#160; It just wasn’t working and then I began to realize that C# already has a pipelining syntax, even if only in one small subset of the .NET API.&#160; You can find a decent pipelining syntax with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fluent_interface" target="_blank">Fluent Interface</a> used for the LINQ extension methods.&#160; Its power is in the fact that the functions return the object type that was passed in and acted upon, so that more functions can be chained on afterward in a composable manner.&#160; The ability to do things like <font face="Courier New">collection.Where().Select().OrderBy()</font> is a much more declarative and functional solution to imperative <font face="Courier New">for</font> loops (and it makes it more readable and intention revealing in my opinion).&#160; It’s a difference in describing more <u><em>what</em></u> you want to be accomplished rather than <em><u>how</u></em> it is to be accomplished (especially when the <u><em>how</em></u> in programming languages is more readable to a computer than it is a human).</p>

  <p>So the good news is that you indeed can have a nice pipelining syntax in C#, especially for APIs that are designed with Fluent Interfaces like LINQ.&#160; However, it doesn’t solve code readability issues with code snippets like the C# fragment I showed above.&#160; For those regular, non-fluent method calls in the rest of the .NET API, you must use old-fashioned Object-Oriented Programming practices of breaking code up into meaningful, atomic units of statements and naming and encapsulating functions cohesively in order to get more readable code.</p>
</span>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jonas Elfström</div>
<div class='content'>
This looks a whole lot like the Thrush Combinator.<br /><a href="http://alicebobandmallory.com/articles/2009/10/06/the-thrush-combinator-in-c" rel="nofollow">I implemented</a> that one in C# a while ago</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Richard Beauchamp</div>
<div class='content'>
This comment has been removed by the author.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mike Murray</div>
<div class='content'>
Funny you should mention the Maybe Monad, as I&#39;ve been looking into Monads off and on for several months trying to figure out how I could use them in everyday code.  I likely will be posting something on this in the somewhat near future.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Just a small hint from someone who uses something like this in productive code on a day-to-day basis:<br /><br />Take your time and extend the static methods a bit. It won&#39;t hurt to build something like a maybe-monad in there.<br /><br />You know - check if the input is null and return null if so.<br /><br />For this you need either:<br />- &quot;where U : class&quot;<br />- use Equals<br /><br />For the same reason I give somethink like a &quot;DefaultValue&quot; Funktion that checks the input for null and responses with the default-value if so, if not it will give the original value.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mike Murray</div>
<div class='content'>
Very intriguing! Man I wish I had thought about that.  I suppose I&#39;m still new to designing APIs that pass around Funcs.<br /><br />I was able to make the following code work with the type inference (and without having to specify the types to the Then method):<br /><br />var blah = &quot;576 &quot;<br />.Then(x =&gt; x.Trim())<br />.Then(x =&gt; Convert.ToInt32(x));<br /><br />Not too bad really.  A little too much C# syntax though, but I&#39;d argue it might be more readable than what we started with, the code everyone writes.  It appears my code snippet doesn&#39;t even need the second extension method.<br /><br />Thanks for sharing!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Yusuf Motara</div>
<div class='content'>
You could try this:<br /><br />static class Extn {<br />    public static U Then&lt;T,U&gt;(this T o, Func&lt;T, U&gt; f) { return f(o); }<br />    public static U Then&lt;T, U&gt;(this T o, Func&lt;T, Func&lt;U&gt;&gt; fe) { return fe(o)(); }<br />}<br /><br />... which lets you write the more-readable:<br /><br />var blah = &quot;576  &quot;<br />   .Then&lt;string,string&gt;(x =&gt; x.Trim)<br />   .Then(Convert.ToInt32);<br /><br />Unfortunately, it seems that you need to make the generic parameters explicit; C#&#39;s type inference is nowhere near as good as F#&#39;s.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Anagram Code Kata Part 5 – Domain Objects Over Language Primitives]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/02/20/anagram-code-kata-part-5-domain-objects-over-language-primitives/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-20T17:55:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/02/20/anagram-code-kata-part-5-domain-objects-over-language-primitives</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>This post is part of a <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/11/anagram-code-kata-bdd-mspec.html">series on coding Kata, BDD, MSpec, and SOLID principles</a>.&#160; Feel free to visit the above link which points to the introductory post, also containing an index of all posts in the series.</p>  <p>In this post, we will discuss some reasons why you might want to avoid using language primitives directly in place of domain objects.&#160; Specifically, I have been using <font face="Courier New">String</font> variables and objects to represent words up to this point.&#160; <a href="http://adotnetdude.blogspot.com/">Esteban</a> suggested I create a <font face="Courier New">Word</font> class for a few good reasons which I’ll layout for you.&#160; Out of sheer luck and good timing, <a href="http://codebetter.com/blogs/dru.sellers/default.aspx">Dru Sellers</a> of <a href="http://codebetter.com/">CodeBetter.com</a> also wrote on this subject shortly afterward and confirmed Esteban’s reasoning.</p> <span class="fullpost">   <h3>Use <font face="Courier New">String</font> Class or Create <font face="Courier New">Word</font> Domain Object?</h3>    <p>I mentioned in the previous post that Esteban had suggested creating a <font face="Courier New">Word</font> class instead of just passing around strings everywhere through my application.&#160; One good reason is that we don’t own the <font face="Courier New">String</font> class and so further modification to our string-based implementation is difficult because the logic is scattered throughout the application, instead of centralized under the responsibility and definition of one domain class.&#160; It is much more difficult to refactor the word-specific logic with its behaviors and attributes spread throughout the code.&#160; Even if your <font face="Courier New">Word</font> class doesn’t grow any more beyond a seemingly unnecessary wrapper of the <font face="Courier New">String</font> class, the code is more cohesive and ready for change should the need arise.</p>    <p>But more importantly, you designed the code thinking in a true object-oriented mindset.&#160; You have to keep in mind that the <font face="Courier New">String</font> class is someone else’s implementation, and is hardly ever sufficient in and of itself as a domain object within your solution.&#160; Think about it, the behaviors that a string object performs are so generic and multipurpose that you likely don’t need two-thirds of the class as defined (and there’s likely a few behaviors you really need that aren’t there).&#160; Of course nearly every application on earth makes use of the <font face="Courier New">String</font> class; but because of this fact, it has no meaning in and of itself within any given application.&#160; You would have to look at how the stings are actually used within the code in order to understand its unique application within the app’s context.&#160; Of course that task of research is much easier for everyone (including the original author of the code) if it’s all encapsulated within a dedicated domain object class.&#160; True object-orientation means describing in code form the properties, behaviors, and interactions/relationships of real world objects within your problem domain.</p>    <p>Esteban gave me a great example to illustrate these points.&#160; He said that you can always represent money as a decimal (and even when you use a domain object, it’s got to have a decimal language primitive underneath the covers).&#160; However, what happens when you need to attach metadata to the amount (like currency denomination), or if you need to change decimal precision?&#160; You would have to go through all of the code and make sure your use of decimal language primitives is modified uniformly in order to retain consistency.&#160; Also, mathematic operations involving money are hardly ever the same as their counterparts involving standard decimals, because currency deals with discrete values to a certain decimal precision.&#160; Typically when the behaviors and properties within our system begin to get complex, we are cognizant enough to create domain objects in order to bring it all under one class.&#160; We definitely don’t want to over-architect features and interactions before we need them, but I think there is power in this principle of abstracting away language primitives and instead encapsulating their use within domain objects located in just one place in your codebase.&#160; I believe it is one thing we can keep in mind to help guide us to better object-oriented thinking, and avoid language-oriented coding.</p>    <p>As mentioned above, Esteban’s thoughts were confirmed nearly verbatim by <a href="http://codebetter.com/blogs/dru.sellers/default.aspx">Dru Sellers</a> of <a href="http://codebetter.com/">CodeBetter.com</a> in his blog post that he wrote just a few days after I had the conversation with Esteban.&#160; A great coincidence no doubt, and worth a read; here’s the link:</p>    <p><a href="http://codebetter.com/blogs/dru.sellers/archive/2010/01/27/business-primitives-1-2.aspx">Business Primitives (1/2)</a>&#160;</p>    <h3><font face="Courier New">Word</font> Class Implementation</h3>    <p>So basically I created the following class implementation and then replaced string with a reference to this new class, <font face="Courier new">Word</font>:</p>    <pre class="brush: csharp">public class Word
{
    private string wordStr = string.Empty;

    public Word(string wordStr)
    {
        this.wordStr = wordStr;
    }

    public override string ToString()
    {
        return wordStr;
    }

    public override bool Equals(object obj)
    {
        return wordStr == ((Word)obj).ToString();
    }

    public override int GetHashCode()
    {
        return base.GetHashCode();
    }

    public int GetCanonicalHashCode()
    {
        char[] letters = wordStr.ToCharArray();
        Array.Sort&lt;char&gt;(letters);
        return new string(letters).GetHashCode();
    }
}</pre>

  <p>I have defined an overridden implementation for <font face="Courier New">Equals(object)</font> (so that the test assertions and other <font face="Courier New">IEnumerable.Contains()</font> queries work) and <font face="Courier New">GetHashCode()</font> (solely to satisfy a compiler warning).&#160; I also moved the <font face="Courier New">GetCanoncialHashCode()</font> method from <font face="Courier New">AnagramGrouper</font>, in order to better encapsulate it as a behavior a Word knows how to do innately.</p>

  <p>One other change I had to make was to convert strings into <font face="Courier New">Word</font> objects in our <font face="Courier New">NewlineFileParser</font>, which I accomplished by using an <font face="Courier New">IEnumberable.Select()</font> call as shown below:</p>

  <pre class="brush: csharp">return File.ReadAllLines(filePath).Select&lt;string, Word&gt;(x =&gt; new Word(x));</pre>

  <p></p>

  <h3>Let’s Revisit <font face="Courier New">AssertWasCalled</font> One More Time</h3>

  <p>Trust me, I am groaning with you, even as I wrote that heading text.&#160; The last thing we need is for me to rehash the topic again and flip flop my stance yet another time.&#160; Yes, that’s right I’ve changed my mind again.&#160; First I couldn’t understand what utility asserting methods were called would have under normal test scenarios.&#160; Then I changed my mind that perhaps using it would help my test specifications have clearer intent of what I am asserting.&#160; After an email conversation with <a href="http://www.davesquared.net/">David Tchepak</a>, I think I’m now back to my original stance.&#160; Here is what Dave said that had me reconsidering, and I think it’s pretty sound reasoning (emphasis added by me):</p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>…</p>

    <p>“But seeing as you asked for it, here goes. :)</p>

    <p>“I try and avoid <font face="Courier New">AssertWasCalled</font> like the plague. Generally I don't care that some method was called, I care that my class does the work it needs to. If that involves calling a dependency then great, but that is not my class' reason for existence.</p>

    <p>“I prefer your original approach of stubbing out everything in the setup and having that tested indirectly. One reason I prefer this is I find it makes it easier to refactor: the assertions in my test don't change, the class still does the same thing. However I can add or change dependencies by changing some wiring in the setup, and then make sure I haven't stuffed anything up as my assertions still pass. <strong>I prefer that my tests specify what I want, not how it does it.</strong> To me, <font face="Courier New">AssertWasCalled</font> reeks of over-specification. The one exception is where I hit the external boundaries of my code, so where I want to send an email or something without side effects that I can test. Then the core of the behaviour is the call itself, so I'm happy to assert on that then.”</p>
  </blockquote>

  <p>And with that I’ll promise to never bring this up again…unless of course I get swayed by someone else. :)&#160; In all seriousness, I think this is an interesting discussion and so if you have insight, please share via comment below.</p>

  <h3>Summary</h3>

  <p>Please leave your thoughts in the comments below in regard to creating domain objects over using language primitives (or heaven forbid, the <font face="Courier New">AssertWasCalled</font> debate).&#160; As far as this coding kata exercise, I need to take a high-level look at where this should go next.&#160; Perhaps the next post will tie up loose ends and see how our code performs on large text files as input.&#160; It may be that we will need to refactor our architecture to achieve better runtimes.&#160; If not, maybe we can still discuss where would could have headed if it had been necessary.</p>
</span>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Anagram Code Kata Part 4 – Will it Write My Code for Me?]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/01/26/anagram-code-kata-part-4-will-it-write-my-code-for-me/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-26T22:27:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/01/26/anagram-code-kata-part-4-will-it-write-my-code-for-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>This post is part of a <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/11/anagram-code-kata-bdd-mspec.html">series on coding Kata, BDD, MSpec, and SOLID principles</a>.&#160; Feel free to visit the above link which points to the introductory post, also containing an index of all posts in the series.</p>  <p>In this post, we work on implementing the other main dependency, <font face="Courier New">IAnagramsFinder</font>.&#160; In doing so, you will discover that I have been a little naïve with this BDD methodology. Apparently I expected a different experience than what I ran into doing the exercise.&#160; In gathering feedback, I had a very interesting discussion about Object-Oriented Programming with <a href="http://adotnetdude.blogspot.com/">Esteban</a> that I will summarize and ask for further discussion from all of you.&#160; I’ll also show you one way to debug your code when running the MSpec tests via the console test runner.</p> <span class="fullpost">   <h3>New Thoughts on Mocks vs. Stubs</h3>    <p>During <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/11/anagram-code-kata-part-2-mocking-and.html">Part 2 of this series</a>, <a href="http://papamufflon.blogspot.com/">Tobias</a> left <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/11/anagram-code-kata-part-2-mocking-and.html#comments">a comment about using mocks and <font face="Courier New">AssertWasCalled</font></a>, rather than stubs and defining fake responses.&#160; I didn’t understand how it would help, as it appeared they would accomplish roughly the same thing.&#160; With stubs and fake responses, if you don’t get back the return you are looking for, then you can infer that the dependencies weren’t called since you had previously hard-coded their return values when called.&#160; With mocks and asserting methods were called, you directly assert that the manager class did in fact call it’s dependencies.</p>    <p>When I looked more closely into using the <font face="Courier New">AssertWasCalled</font> method in Rhino.Mocks, I noticed that my strategy of using stubs and faked return values wasn’t very explicit in signifying that the ultimate responsibility of the manager class was to delegate to its dependencies.&#160; I mean the test context does rigorously stub out the dependencies, but the actual assertions weren’t clear what we were testing.&#160; Therefore, I decided to pop in a pair of <font face="Courier New">AssertWasCalled</font> statements (as found below), leaving <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/11/anagram-code-kata-part-2-mocking-and.html#firstSpec">the rest of the test the same as it was back in Part 2</a>.</p>    <pre class="brush: csharp">It should_result_in_list_of_anagram_sets_and_both_dependencies_should_have_been_called = () =&gt;
{
    fileParser.AssertWasCalled(x =&gt; x.ExtractWordListFromFile(filePath));
    anagramGrouper.AssertWasCalled(x =&gt; x.FindAnagramSets(wordListFromFile));

    result.ShouldEqual(expected);
};</pre>

  <p>However, when I thought to simplify the test code by removing most of stubbing setup, it appeared I had to leave most of the stub logic in tact in order to test if <font face="Courier New">anagramGrouper.FindAnagramSets()</font> was called with parameter <font face="Courier New">wordListFromFile</font>, which was one of the stubbed fake responses.&#160; The one dependency (the file parser) needed to pass it’s return value to the next dependency (the anagrams finder).&#160; I could not think of a way to accomplish testing that the manager class facilitated that without the stubbing logic (fake responses) that I created.</p>

  <p>It would be great if someone could enlighten me since I’m such a newbie to mocking and stubbing.&#160; Otherwise, I feel the intent of the test is now more clear with the <font face="Courier New">AssertWasCalled</font> checks that I added, even if that I means I’m needlessly mixing stubbing and mocking.&#160; But one last question:&#160; should I try to stick more closely to the rule of thumb guiding me to stick to one all-encompassing assertion per test if possible?&#160; Let me know your thoughts.</p>

  <h3>Implementing the <font face="Courier New">AnagramGrouper</font> Dependency</h3>

  <p>So let’s continue onward with some more actual design and code.&#160; We are tackling the <font face="Courier New">AnagramGrouper</font> dependency, whose sole responsibility is to take in the parsed collection of words and find anagram sets.&#160; Here is the test spec (one thing to note is that in some of my earlier tests for the <font face="Courier New">AnagramsFinder</font> manager class and <font face="Courier New">IFileParser</font>, I had used string arrays liberally; I decided to go with <font face="Courier New">IList&lt;string&gt;</font> collections instead):</p>

  <pre class="brush: csharp">public class AnagramGrouperSpecs
{
    [Subject(typeof(AnagramGrouperSpecs))]
    public class when_given_word_list_collection
    {
        static AnagramGrouper sut;
        static IEnumerable&lt;IList&lt;string&gt;&gt; result;
        static IEnumerable&lt;string&gt; wordList = new[] { &quot;wordA&quot;, &quot;wordB&quot;, &quot;Aword&quot;, &quot;wordC&quot; };

        Establish context = () =&gt;
        {
            sut = new AnagramGrouper();
        };

        Because of = () =&gt;
        {
            result = sut.FindAnagramSets(wordList);
        };

        It should_result_in_anagram_sets_collection_of_length_1 = () =&gt;
        {
            result.Count().ShouldEqual(1);
        };

        It should_contain_2_specific_words_in_the_anagram_set = () =&gt;
        {
            result.First().ShouldContain(&quot;wordA&quot;, &quot;Aword&quot;);
        };
    }
}</pre>

  <p>Here too I have basically two assertions (but split it up differently than last time); should I also try harder to avoid this as well?</p>

  <p>When contemplating how to further breakdown this responsibility of finding anagram sets into subtasks, I figure we would need one piece of code that would compare two words and answer whether they are anagrams of each other, and another piece of code that would keep track of the various anagram sets (perhaps a collection or dictionary of string arrays).&#160; With what BDD has revealed to me thus far, I figure this means we are going to see two more dependencies (and interfaces, and spec tests) added to the codebase.</p>

  <p>So I start with the word comparison task, thinking I could perhaps leverage the <font face="Courier New">String.GetHashCode()</font> method for assigning meaningful value to the list of characters in the string.&#160; However, string hash codes give importance to letter casing and order of characters, so a modified strategy would have to be utilized, even though <font face="Courier New">GetHashCode()</font> seems quite close to filling our need.</p>

  <p>Now I probably should have come up with this ingenious algorithm all by myself, but…it is what it is and this is the best, most concise solution that I can put together to solve the problem.&#160; With that said, I ended up doing some internet searching in order to proof-of-concept my <font face="Courier New">GetHashCode()</font> idea.&#160; I came across pure genius in the form of <a href="http://www.formatexception.com/">Brian Mullen’s</a> blog post entitled <a href="http://www.formatexception.com/2009/03/linq-group-by-and-groupby/">LINQ group by and GroupBy</a>, specifically the second-to-last code snippet.&#160; Just <font face="Courier New">String.ToCharArray()</font> the word and then <font face="Courier New">Array.Sort()</font> the resultant array; now turn it back into a string and do <font face="Courier New">GetHashCode()</font> now.&#160; (As a side note, we can worry about case-insensitivity later if desired by simply doing a <font face="Courier New">String.ToLower()</font> on the word before getting the hash code.)&#160; Now anagrams will have the same hash code (Brian uses the term “canonical”, which I think is very fitting); it’s literally perfect in every way!</p>

  <p>So now for the other dependency, I figure we could use a <font face="Courier New">Dictionary&lt;int, IList&lt;string&gt;&gt;</font>, where the key is the canonical hash code and the value is a string list collection representing an anagram set of words.&#160; These two dependency implementations are so simple and straight forward that I have a hard time seeing a reason to continue breaking out full-fledged object dependencies with interfaces and Dependency Injection.&#160; However, I will make a case for moving the canonical hash code logic outside this <font face="Courier New">AnagramsGrouper</font> class, but that will come later.</p>

  <p>So let’s write some code to pass our test/spec:</p>

  <pre class="brush: csharp">public class AnagramGrouper : IAnagramGrouper
{
    public IEnumerable&lt;IList&lt;string&gt;&gt; FindAnagramSets(IEnumerable&lt;string&gt; wordList)
    {
        Dictionary&lt;int, IList&lt;string&gt;&gt; results = new Dictionary&lt;int, IList&lt;string&gt;&gt;();

        foreach (string word in wordList)
        {
            int canonicalHashCode = GetCanonicalHashCode(word);

            if (results.ContainsKey(canonicalHashCode))
            {
                results[canonicalHashCode].Add(word);
            }
            else
            {
                results.Add(canonicalHashCode, new List&lt;string&gt;(new[] { word }));
            }
        }

        return results.Values;
    }

    public static int GetCanonicalHashCode(string word)
    {
        char[] letters = word.ToCharArray();
        Array.Sort&lt;char&gt;(letters);

        return new string(letters).GetHashCode();
    }
}</pre>

  <p>Maybe you noticed already, but there is a bug in my logic.&#160; At that time, I didn’t see it and needed to debug the code while running.&#160; Setting a debug break point in your code doesn’t work like you’re probably used to, and this is because we’re running the MSpec tests via its console test runner.&#160; I had to do some searching to figure this one out, and that’s what we’ll cover next.</p>

  <h3>How to Debug MSpec Specifications and the Code They Test</h3>

  <p>After a short ride on the Google super highway, I found a <a href="http://codebetter.com/blogs/aaron.jensen/archive/2008/09/02/mspec-v0-2.aspx#comments">blog post containing a November 2009 comment</a> from <a href="http://codebetter.com/blogs/aaron.jensen/default.aspx">Aaron Jensen</a>, author of MSpec, that gave a few possible solutions.&#160; I opted to go with the <font face="Courier new">Debugger.Break()</font> solution, which I put at the very top of my <font face="Courier new">FindAnagramSets</font> method.&#160; It is a tad awkward because it will show a Windows error dialog box that says the program encountered a problem and Windows is searching the web for a solution.&#160; If you wait through that, it will give you an option to debug the program via a Visual Studio dialog where you select the currently running instance of Visual Studio as your debugger instance.&#160; You just remove the statement when you’re done (and you’ll really want to remember to remove it from your production code).&#160; Does the trick, though it is a bit obtrusive to your code base.</p>

  <p>If you haven’t already figured it out, the bug is that my <font face="Courier New">FindAnagramSets</font> method is returning all anagram sets found in the dictionary.&#160; An anagram set of just one word is not really an anagram set, which is why our test specification which is based on that assumption failed.&#160; The fix is to filter out anagram word sets with less than two words before returning, like this:</p>

  <pre class="brush: csharp">// Return anagram sets with more than one word in it
return results.Values.Where(x =&gt; x.Count &gt; 1);</pre>

  <p>That will make the code pass the tests now.&#160; Remember to remove the debugger statement we added.</p>

  <h3>BDD, OOP…WTH?!</h3>

  <p>Just kidding.&#160; But I do want to discuss a reaction I had to BDD after implementing this anagram finding solution.&#160; After I completed the code and finished the tests, I was feeling pretty great.&#160; But then I started thinking about how I didn’t really go down the path that I felt BDD was originally trying to lead me down with <font face="Courier New">AnagramGrouper</font>, which was to create two more dependencies, just as I had done for the first managing class <font face="Courier New">AnagramsFinder</font>.&#160; I mean I felt pretty frustrated because I was digging BDD to this point.&#160; I’m not quite sure what my original expectations were, but I might have thought BDD was magically going to right my algorithms for me as well.</p>

  <p>I decided to discuss the whole thing with <a href="http://adotnetdude.blogspot.com/">Esteban</a> to get some perspective on the issue.&#160; He told me he didn’t know a thing about BDD and how it’s supposed to work, but he figured BDD would lead me to decoupled, cohesive code design, but he couldn’t see how it would aide with algorithmic solutions to the problems at hand.&#160; I’m not sure why I was so naïve, but it makes complete sense.&#160; I mean these methodologies are designed to keep you disciplined to some proven, guiding principles, but you still need to use your brain and creativity to actually solve the problem.&#160; I guess it would help to get some feedback and suggestions from you all in regard to knowing when it is time to switch from BDD architecture design mode to algorithm design mode within the broken down dependencies that handle the very specific sub-responsibilities.&#160; Please let me know if you have found some guiding concept or question you’ve come up with that you put to the test in order to lead you into the right coding mindset for that particular context (design or algorithm; or do I even have the right categories?).</p>

  <p>Perhaps it’s just that this design process feels so new to me.&#160; Maybe I have solely been in the coding, algorithm mindset this whole time throughout my career.&#160; Perhaps it will become more natural with practice and experience.&#160; I guess it just feels like I’m learning to drive a manual, stick-shift car or something, and I am a little rough with the clutch when transitioning between gears.</p>

  <p>To take this discussion further, <a href="http://adotnetdude.blogspot.com/">Esteban</a> made a comment in our conversation about his personal thoughts on these methodologies (like BDD) and Object-Oriented Programming.&#160; He has come to believe that we invent these methodologies like flavors of the week “because as programmers we don’t really get OOP.”&#160; Perhaps OOP just comes more naturally to his thought process that most people (or he admits it’s possible he could just be completely ignorant), but he feels that there’s really just a few simple rules and guidelines to keep in mind at all times in order to keep your objects behaving like real life objects and not acting like data constructs.&#160; I encouraged him to give his theory some additional thought and make it a little more formal by writing it down.&#160; He did this and the following is a link to the resultant blog post:</p>

  <p><a href="http://adotnetdude.blogspot.com/2010/01/3-simple-rules-to-good-object-oriented.html">3 Simple Rules to Good Object Oriented Code</a></p>

  <p>Please read through that post and comment on it.&#160; His idea needs to be criticized and/or validated.&#160; He admits he may have no clue what he’s talking about, but I said that’s why it needs to be put to the test by posting it in the open.&#160; We both think it’s an interesting theory, but we’re unsure if it even holds any water.&#160; Perhaps Esteban’s theory is too simplistic to be practical for many programmers.&#160; Provide feedback and lots of it.</p>

  <h3>Summary</h3>

  <p>So I think I need to wrap this post up about now.&#160; I think I have raised enough discussion points to write a book, but please do take the time to comment on what I’m doing wrong, what I’m doing right, or how to make the BDD mentality more flowing and natural.&#160; I promised to talk about having a Word class as opposed to using primitive strings everywhere, and that will definitely be in the next post.&#160; Also, I think our <font face="Courier New">AnagramGrouper</font> class may need some more testing and flushing out of how it should handle spaces, punctuation, casing, and so on.</p>

  <p>Thanks for sticking with me thus far.</p>
</span>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Anagram Code Kata Part 3 – Use Common Sense]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/12/18/anagram-code-kata-part-3-use-common-sense/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-18T18:10:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2009/12/18/anagram-code-kata-part-3-use-common-sense</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>This post is part of a <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/11/anagram-code-kata-bdd-mspec.html">series on coding Kata, BDD, MSpec, and SOLID principles</a>.&#160; Feel free to visit the above link which points to the introductory post, also containing an index of all posts in the series.</p>  <p>In this post, we will discuss how far to take the idea of creating mockable contracts via interfaces for testing purposes and to keep responsibilities modular.&#160; As I solicited feedback from commenters, I was getting hung up on applying this concept to every object and dependency.&#160; We’ll talk about how I’m now thinking that overly strict adherence to the practice can drive you nuts and decrease productivity.&#160; It is meant to help guide your design process along rather than hinder it.&#160; We’ll finish this post off with one of our two dependencies implemented in an extremely simple manner.</p> <span class="fullpost">   <h3><font face="Courier New">IFileParser</font> Dependency</h3>    <p>When we left off last time, we had defined two separate responsibilities that <font face="Courier New">AnagramsFinder</font> was going to push down into its dependencies.&#160; As I started to write a specification test for the newly created <font face="Courier New">NewlineFileParser</font>, I realized it would be difficult to stub based on providing a file path to a text file as the only parameter.&#160; I began having thoughts that maybe I could break up another pair of dependencies for file parsing, namely obtaining a file stream (or file contents string) from a path and then parsing the file contents into a list of multiple lines.&#160; But then again, my first of the two dependencies is still dependent on the physical file system and I cannot get away from this unless I somehow mock up an in-memory file system.&#160; This began to feel silly to me as I was hoping I would just use the built-in .NET APIs for file systems and string parsing.</p>    <p>After emailing <a href="http://www.davesquared.net/" target="_blank">Dave</a> and <a href="http://adotnetdude.blogspot.com/" target="_blank">Esteban</a> asking for guidance, the revelation I received via these two fine gentlemen is that file parsing is not an essential purpose of this application nor exercise (at least not yet; we won’t be focusing on performance unless it appears to be grossly deficient as we go along).&#160; What we could do is write integration tests instead, where we have a set of simple test files sitting in a folder that we run our <font face="Courier New">NewlineFileParser</font> against to ensure it working as we expect.&#160; But I don’t think I’m even going to do this at this point.&#160; I really do want to get to the core of the application.&#160; Plus, I feel certain that I can trust the implementation of <font face="Courier New">File.ReadAllLines()</font> from the .NET Framework.</p>    <p>Unless it needs to be changed further down the road, the following code implementation will likely be sufficient for the remainder of this coding exercise:</p>    <pre class="brush: csharp">public class NewlineFileParser : IFileParser
{
    public IEnumerable&lt;string&gt; ExtractWordListFromFile(string filePath)
    {
        return File.ReadAllLines(filePath);
    }
}</pre>

  <p>I feel great about this because I haven’t gone insane trying to mock and test everything in sight, nor have I broken up every single responsibility in such small chunks that it becomes tedious.&#160; Instead, I have broken up the two core responsibilities of <font face="Courier New">AnagramsFinder</font> which means I can change and test the two dependencies independent of each other and from their manager class.&#160; Even though I haven’t written a ton of code yet, I feel the tests specs have driven my design into a cohesive, decoupled design that should prove flexible if requirements change or if I encounter friction later on and need to rethink my design.&#160; A flexible architecture for the application is being flushed out based on a “top-to-bottom” design view of the requirements.</p>

  <h3>Create Stubs or Assert Methods were Called</h3>

  <p><a href="http://papamufflon.blogspot.com/">Tobias Walter</a> left <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/11/anagram-code-kata-part-2-mocking-and.html#comments">a comment on my last post</a> with some suggestions that I would like to get clarification on and discuss further with my growing audience of three now.&#160; He compared some of my implementation to <a href="http://www.davesquared.net/2009/11/favour-test-driving-logic-over-data.html">Dave’s implementation on his Favour test driving logic over data post</a>, but the comparison was lost on me.&#160; It seemed Tobias was saying that I had gone too far breaking up the responsibilities into such small dependencies.&#160; I am unsure what his argument was, but as far as I could tell both Dave and I broke up a managing class into two separate responsibilities so that the more crucial of the two could be tested independently.&#160; Also in doing so, we both created stubs that were given specific dummy responses to method calls using Rhino.Mocks.&#160; One more comment I would like to say is that I broke the file parsing responsibility away into its own dependency more because of the need to isolate the anagrams grouping than because file parsing is of itself a difficult task.&#160; If Tobias or anyone else could try to clarify his argument, that would really help me understand the merits of his suggestions.</p>

  <p>Another suggestion that Tobias brought up that I would like to petition feedback on is to use the mocking feature of testing whether a method was called instead of creating a stub programmed with a dummy response.&#160; I have to admit, I’m not sure when to use one method over another.&#160; I guess I’ve felt in the past that testing whether a method was called seems silly, since it seems odd to have your test know the implementation and inner method calls of the subject under test.&#160; But I am now realizing that my stubs appear to be doing the same thing, but with dummy input and output programmed in.&#160; If you have an opinion or experience on this subject, please leave some feedback in the comments of this post.</p>

  <h3>What’s Next?</h3>

  <p>In my next post I hope to summarize this mocking debate brought up above regarding two differing methods of verifying my manager class is correctly managing its dependencies.&#160; I also hope to begin driving out the design and implementation of the <font face="Courier New">AnagramGrouper</font> dependency via behavior specification tests.&#160; Thanks and any feedback is greatly appreciated.</p>
</span>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>David</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi Mike,<br /><br />In terms of the stubbing vs. asserting a method was called, the team I&#39;m on has found we rarely AssertWasCalled any more. Doing so explicitly couples our tests/specs to the implementation, whereas just stubbing calls in a SetUp seems easier to change without altering the fundamental assertions in our tests. <br /><br />The only time we use AssertWasCalled is for void methods to a service or similar where there is no observable side-effect from a unit perspective.<br /><br />YMMV. :)<br /><br />Regards,<br />David</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Tobias Walter</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi Mike,<br /><br />great you continued this series.<br /><br />I think I messed things up and wrote incorrect things. In the meantime I managed to do this kata again and now I agree with you. Just forget my advice to mock it - this was wrong.<br /><br />However, I and my coworkers question if it&#39;s worth to write 30 lines of code to test a 2-lines-method? I think for this kata it will be enough to do some acceptance tests here.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
