<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: News and Politics | Mike Murray]]></title>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/categories/news-and-politics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-08T21:27:17-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://mkmurray.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Murray]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Irena Sendler's Story]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2008/08/08/irena-sendler-s-story/"/>
    <updated>2008-08-08T15:04:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2008/08/08/irena-sendler-s-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Again, I promise I won't do this very often (since this is a programming blog), but the world needs to know...</p>  <p>Irena Sendler (<a title="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irena_Sendler" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irena_Sendler">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irena_Sendler</a>), a Polish Catholic social worker, risked her very own life to save 2,500 Jewish children from certain death at the hands of the Nazi genocide.&#160; She did it by smuggling the children out of the Warsaw ghettos and placing them in new homes with new identities.&#160; Then when the Holocaust was over, she spent her life reuniting these children with loved ones and extended family members (because many of the children's parents had been executed).</p>  <p>An amazing woman, worthy of an amazing recognition.&#160; The Nobel Peace Prize would be fitting, wouldn't you say?&#160; It is awarded &quot;to the person who shall have done the most or the best work for fraternity between nations, for the abolition or reduction of standing armies, and for the holding and promotion of peace congresses.&quot;</p>  <p>She was indeed nominated for the prize in 2007.&#160; However, she lost...and guess who won instead?&#160; A propagandist and environmental alarmist, who has placed himself in a position to benefit greatly (financially and politically) from the &quot;Green Movement&quot; (in truth, it is nothing more than a <u>theory</u> that greenhouse gases are the cause of Global Warming).&#160; Al Gore won the Nobel Peace Prize for creating a slide show movie.&#160; I think I would be less irritated if he had won for his invention of the Internet or something.</p>  <p>Here is a tribute to Irena Sendler that everyone should watch:&#160; </p> <span class='fullpost'> <div class="wlWriterEditableSmartContent" id="scid:5737277B-5D6D-4f48-ABFC-DD9C333F4C5D:425be2e7-e30a-43d8-aa56-48a65b862f90" style="padding-right: 0px; display: inline; padding-left: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px; margin: 0px; padding-top: 0px"><div id="cb495db8-dacb-4ed8-8fc6-6bfa1b5bc49d" style="margin: 0px; padding: 0px; display: inline;"><div><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OVw1PANUcdg" target="_new"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_rps657FzHZ0/SujVvA5fjrI/AAAAAAAAADI/P1YlI2mylCg/videod77a2dbc4c7a.jpg?imgmax=800" style="border-style: none" galleryimg="no" width="340" height="280" onload="var downlevelDiv = document.getElementById('cb495db8-dacb-4ed8-8fc6-6bfa1b5bc49d'); downlevelDiv.innerHTML = &quot;&lt;div&gt;&lt;object width=\&quot;340\&quot; height=\&quot;280\&quot;&gt;&lt;param name=\&quot;movie\&quot; value=\&quot;http://www.youtube.com/v/OVw1PANUcdg\&quot;&gt;&lt;\/param&gt;&lt;param name=\&quot;wmode\&quot; value=\&quot;transparent\&quot;&gt;&lt;\/param&gt;&lt;embed src=\&quot;http://www.youtube.com/v/OVw1PANUcdg\&quot; type=\&quot;application/x-shockwave-flash\&quot; wmode=\&quot;transparent\&quot; width=\&quot;340\&quot; height=\&quot;280\&quot;&gt;&lt;\/embed&gt;&lt;\/object&gt;&lt;\/div&gt;&quot;;" alt=""></a></div></div></div>  <p>The question I have to ask is how can Al Gore accept the Nobel Peace Prize, knowing that he was up against a real hero and freedom fighter?&#160; She risked her life for peace and saved 2,500 Jewish children.&#160; Al Gore has done nothing but shoot off his mouth.&#160; How can he even think he deserved the prize more than her?&#160; Why didn't he decline the prize and offer up the name of Irena instead?&#160; Because it didn't quite fit into his political agenda.</p>  <p>On behalf of those that can appreciate true selfless and compassionate service to mankind, I have just four words for Irena Sendler:</p>  <p>Thank you so much.</p> </span>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
The 2007 Nobel Peace Prize was shared.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Expelled - An Investigative Documentary]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2008/04/17/expelled-an-investigative-documentary/"/>
    <updated>2008-04-17T14:22:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2008/04/17/expelled-an-investigative-documentary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p></p>  <p>So I won't stray from programming entries very often on this blog unless there is something really important I feel needs to be said.</p>  <p>I, for one, am tired of the Michael Moore documentaries that do nothing but complain about how crappy our nation is.&#160; I also am not a fan of Al Gore's biased misrepresentation of the facts about Global Warming and his claims that the whole scientific community is behind him; I personally think he doesn't care about Global Warming all that much and just loves all this attention and wealth that he is accumulating.&#160; But that is a discussion for another time and place...</p>  <p>Well, to keep this brief, there is a new documentary coming out in movie theaters around the nation tomorrow by Ben Stein.&#160; It is called <u>Expelled</u>, and it is an investigative documentary around the systematic persecution by &quot;Big Science&quot; against anyone who questions the theory of Darwinism and proposes the idea that there might have been Intelligent Design.&#160; The movie is a campaign to convince &quot;Big Science&quot; of their close-mindedness, and I support this movement and hope it succeeds.</p>  <p>Here are some links if you are interested further:</p>  <ul>   <li>Trailer:&#160; <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xGCxbhGaVfE">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xGCxbhGaVfE</a> </li>    <li>Movie Theater Locater:&#160; <a title="http://www.expelledthemovie.com/theaterap.php" href="http://www.expelledthemovie.com/theaterap.php">http://www.expelledthemovie.com/theaterap.php</a> </li>    <li>2 Official Web Sites:      <ul>       <li><a href="http://www.getexpelled.com/">http://www.getexpelled.com/</a> </li>        <li><a href="http://www.expelledthemovie.com/">http://www.expelledthemovie.com/</a> </li>     </ul>   </li> </ul>  <p>Ok, back to programming now!</p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
