<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: C# | Mike Murray]]></title>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/categories/c-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mkmurray.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-29T14:47:08-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mkmurray.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Murray]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FubuMVC Webinar - Compositional and Convention-based Web Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/07/21/fubumvc-webinar-compositional-and-convention-based-web-development/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-21T12:44:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/07/21/fubumvc-webinar-compositional-and-convention-based-web-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I just gave a webinar yesterday for <a href="http://www.jpboodhoo.com/">JP Boodhoo’s</a> <a href="http://webinars.developwithpassion.com/">Develop With Passion® webinar series</a> on Compositional and Convention-based Web Development with <a href="http://fubumvc.com/">FubuMVC</a>. The recorded session is now posted online with a slew of referenced and related links. I apologize for the sound quality and will make corrections if I get another chance to do another webinar/screencast. Here is the link to the recording:</p>  <p><a href="http://webinars.developwithpassion.com/webinars/3">http://webinars.developwithpassion.com/webinars/3</a></p>  <p>I didn’t mention this in the screencast but before we began switching our company’s production website to FubuMVC, we first devised a way to get the benefit of <a href="http://murrayon.net/2011/06/fubumvc-behavior-chains-bmvc-pattern.html">FubuMVC Behavior Chains</a> while still on the ASP.NET MVC framework. Please feel free to read more about that successful venture at <a href="http://paceyourself.net/">Bob Pace’s</a> <a href="http://paceyourself.net/2011/06/11/mvctofubu---transition-your-website-from-aspnet-mvc-to-fubumvc-part-1/">blog post on the MvcToFubu project</a>.</p>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FubuMVC Behavior Chains - The BMVC Pattern]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/06/13/fubumvc-behavior-chains-the-bmvc-pattern/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-13T16:01:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/06/13/fubumvc-behavior-chains-the-bmvc-pattern</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>For the last several months at work, we have been gradually migrating our production website to use the .NET open source <a href="http://fubumvc.com/" target="_blank">FubuMVC web framework</a>. Before committing to a whole new infrastructure for our site, some brilliant talent on our team decided to improve our experience on the ASP.NET MVC framework by integrating in one of FubuMVC’s most compelling features, behavior chains. <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/bob_pace" target="_blank">Bob Pace</a> originally blogged about the process in a two part blog post series (<a href="http://paceyourself.net/2010/08/06/integrating-fubumvc-with-aspnet-mvc-part-1/" target="_blank">part 1</a> and <a href="http://paceyourself.net/2010/08/13/integrating-fubumvc-with-aspnet-mvc-part-2/" target="_blank">part 2</a>); since then, he has <a href="https://github.com/bobpace/MvcToFubu" target="_blank">created a packaged solution called MvcToFubu</a> which he <a href="http://paceyourself.net/2011/06/11/mvctofubu---transition-your-website-from-aspnet-mvc-to-fubumvc-part-1/" target="_blank">just recently started another blog post series about</a>.</p>  <p>Behavior chains are by far my favorite feature of FubuMVC. I believe they single-handedly revolutionized our use of the MVC pattern in a web environment. In fact, I like to think of it as a whole new pattern, the <strong>BMVC Pattern</strong> (I was told by a coworker that the ‘B’ should stand for “Better”, and while that’s true, I’ll stick with “Behaviors”). No, I’m not sincerely trying to coin yet another design or architectural pattern buzzword. However, I am most sincerely not joking when I say behavior chains add a whole new dimension to how I design web architectures. I find myself creating composable pipelines of cohesive, testable components in lieu of monolithic controllers and actions.</p> <span class="fullpost">   <h3>What are Behavior Chains?</h3>    <p>Have you ever looked at your controller actions and thought “Man, there’s a lot going on here!” (validation, authorization, transactions, ORM setup, logging, caching, etc.)? If you haven’t, I urge you to take a conscious look at your controller actions and try to identify code that doesn’t <u>directly</u> relate to the purpose of the page (or sub-view of the page). Shouldn’t there be a way to move some of this secondary infrastructure code out of our controller actions and have it be applied conventionally to the correct actions/routes? Yes, and this is exactly what Behavior Chains are meant to accomplish, the ability to create composable pipelines of reusable behavior nodes for each route in your site.</p>    <p>Behavior chains can be built up in any order you want for each route via Conventions and Policies, which are extension points that allow you to inspect and modify the entire Behavior Graph that was built by FubuMVC during startup bootstrapping. The behavior graph is the modifiable collection of all behavior chains in the site, initially built with just a few default behavior nodes for each route. A typical behavior chain by default usually has an ActionCall node (representing the call to a controller action) and an Output node (often a tie-in to a view rendering engine, but can also be JSON or anything else). Other behavior nodes can be sprinkled into the pipeline in any order in front of or in between the ActionCall and the Output nodes. As mentioned before via the use of Conventions and Policies, it is common practice to filter your list of behavior chains using LINQ extension methods and then add a specific behavior node into the matching chains at a specific location in the chain. This truly elevates coding to conventions to a new level; some of the filtering criteria regarding controller actions that you may come up with could be as follows:</p>    <ul>     <li>Action method names that contain a certain word. </li>      <li>Actions methods that are located in a particular controller or namespace. </li>      <li>Action method signatures that contain an input/output model that implements a specific interface. </li>      <li>Action method signatures that contain an input/output model that contains a property of a certain type or have a particular C# attribute applied to it. </li>      <li>So on, so forth…whatever you can dream up! </li>   </ul>    <p>One more aspect of behavior chains that is important to point out is the logistics in how behavior nodes are chained together. The chains are not merely a linked-list of behavior nodes that are traversed linearly. Instead the makeup of the chains is better conceptualized to be an outer behavior node wrapping around an inner behavior node, which is then itself an outer node wrapped around another inner node, and so on. In fact, the FubuMVC developers like to refer to this chaining architecture as the Onion Layer Model or the Russian Doll Model (conjuring up a mental image of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matryoshka_doll">nesting Russian doll toy called a matryoshka doll or a babushka doll</a>). When an outer behavior node has finished executing it’s logic, it can then optionally execute it’s inner behavior node logic (or stop the behavior chain entirely in order to return early with a response, an error, or even transfer to a different route and behavior chain). One of the key advantages that this wrapping architecture can afford is the ability for an outer behavior to run additional logic or clean up code after all inner behavior nodes have completed (i.e., transactions can be committed, connections can be closed, sessions can be disposed, etc.).</p>    <h3>How does this change the way I code my controllers?</h3>    <p>I find that my controller actions are much thinner and more focused on the base case and the successful code path. All the exceptional code paths and edge cases have been identified and deal with by the other behavior nodes in the chain, prior to my action call being invoked. My action call can now focus on the essential logic that differentiate this route from others. That essential logic doesn’t get lost anymore in the necessary infrastructure code that should be a secondary concern. And all of this logic can be broken up into cohesive, reusable components within a flexible request/response pipeline that can be built up automatically by coding to whatever conventions you deem beneficial. Behavior chains really do add a whole new first-class citizen to the MVC design pattern. Do yourself a favor and check out the MvcToFubu solution mentioned at the top of this post, and bring some FubuMVC behavior chain goodness to your ASP.NET MVC website. I think you might be as impressed as we were and yearn for <a href="http://lostechies.com/chadmyers/2011/05/30/cool-stuff-in-fubucore-and-fubumvc-series/">the other killer features of FubuMVC</a> as well.</p> </span>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mike Murray</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks for thought! Perhaps I&#39;ll post on the mailing list and see what others think about it being involved in the FubuMVC documentation somewhere.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Rex</div>
<div class='content'>
Great post, I didn&#39;t see this one when I was writing my post about authentication behavior. This is a great explanation of behavior chains in FubuMVC.<br /><br />This would also be a great intro to behaviors for the fubumvc guides.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Develop with Passion bootcamp course - Denver 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/05/31/develop-with-passion-bootcamp-course-denver-2011/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-31T09:27:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2011/05/31/develop-with-passion-bootcamp-course-denver-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p><a href="http://paceyourself.net/" target="_blank">A very talented coworker</a> and I recently went to JP Boodhoo’s <a href="http://www.jpboodhoo.com/training.oo" target="_blank">Develop with Passion bootcamp training course</a> (previously known as Nothin but .NET). I had originally heard of the course from <a href="http://www.davesquared.net/" target="_blank">Dave Tchepak</a> who <a href="http://www.davesquared.net/2009/08/nothin-but-net-sydney-2009-day-1.html" target="_blank">attended the course nearly two years ago</a>. This blog post is a wrap-up of my thoughts and feelings about the course itself, <a href="http://www.jpboodhoo.com/" target="_blank">JP Boodhoo</a> as the instructor &amp; experienced craftsman, and the .NET development community in general.</p> <span class="fullpost">   <p>My prior impressions of the course from what I had read was that I would be in awe of JP's coding and design skills and very overwhelmed with the feeling that I didn't really know how to code; also that I would get no sleep at all that week, going from early morning to past midnight every day. I had also heard from a previous course member (off the record) that JP’s organization and direction with course material was a bit disorganized back then (luckily this has changed significantly since he had taken the course). I was really excited to see some good BDD in action, get my TDD passion ignited again (I had actually mentioned on twitter recently that my motivation for test was waning as of late), and see JP's mad Vim skills (since I have gotten into that the last few months).</p>    <p>Overall, I was pleasantly surprised with the fulfillment of most of my positive expectations and initial impressions going into the course. JP's personality and passion are infectious, and his teaching skills are pretty top-notch. The course material was well-structured and there was a clear direction for what we hoped to cover throughout the week (and yet, he was still flexible enough to be able to briefly entertain an off-topic direction the students wanted to take the course). He stayed true to the advertised 9am-9pm every day no matter what. He said that when he did the late nighters with previous courses, people came back the next day with little sleep and trashed as far as coding &amp; learning capabilities go.</p>    <p>Watching him code so efficiently is quite a treat. He automates anything he does more than once so that a particular task doesn’t ever get in his way and hold him back the next time. His <a href="http://www.autohotkey.com/" target="_blank">AutoHotkey</a> scripts and automation tools that he has put together are absolutely incredible. He briefly touched the mouse two times the entire week, and it only for when one of his programs or Windows VM was wigging out. Screens and dialogs flew by so fast, you could tell he wasn't going to let any UI (even Visual Studio) get in the way of his productivity to code. He mentioned he will be open sourcing some of his scripts that he uses to keep his development environment consistent across OS platforms. Definitely cool stuff.</p>    <p>As far as JP's actual coding/design skills, I am absolutely floored. He certainly understands C# and .NET well. But it's his Object-Oriented design skills that blew us away. I've realized I don't really know OO design. I think too mechanically about the implementation of the solution instead of focusing on breaking down the problem into smaller manageable chunks. His TDD skills (both Top Down Design and Test Driven Development) are amazing. I've never been a fan of the TDD samples and intros I've seen (where the instructors do the absolute dumbest thing to make the test pass; JP admitted that style didn’t jive with him either). I've always thought that Behavior Driven Development and Top-Down Design were the way to go if I were to have tests drive my designs (or have tests at all for that matter; I'm still having trouble finding enthusiasm for tests written after development for modules and units). So it was great to see a master at that particular craft. It made me excited to use tests as a tool to guide my OO design, behavior discovery, and problem solving.</p>    <p>Some of you may recall that I had <a href="http://murrayon.net/2009/11/anagram-code-kata-bdd-mspec.html" target="_blank">previously investigated BDD, Machine.Specifications, and Top-Down Design a year and a half ago doing the Anagram Code Kata</a>. I think I can recognize better design and responsibility break-up and assignment nowadays. I likely will blog on these subjects again this year with new &amp; improved passion and knowledge.</p>    <p>There was one sad takeaway for me personally from the course, which was a sense of disappointment in the .NET development community in general. Giving myself some time since the course to really think it through, I’m realizing I’m probably being too tough on our community, as I know each Dev community out there suffers from it’s own set of problems. But I don’t want to excuse our shortcomings either; rather, I would like to point them out so that we can focus on them and root those weaknesses out. I think our community in specific is unique in that there is a big shot company that dictates the direction our community should take, sometimes taking credit for all the innovation. Things are improving lately no doubt; it appears Microsoft is listening more and more and trying to let outsiders get involved and contribute.</p>    <p>But we as .NET devs need to step up and take matters into our own hands, we need to take better control of the code we write and encourage best practices within the realms of our responsibilities and influence. I believe many .NET shops rely on the tools sent down from above so heavily that we don’t really solve problems anymore. JP’s focus on problem solving and code katas from the course attack this deficiency at its core. I do somewhat blame our university Computer Science programs for not teaching real OO (a great discussion on formalism versus hermeneutics in a book I highly recommend, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Object-Thinking-DV-Microsoft-Professional-David/dp/0735619654" target="_blank">Object Thinking</a>), but at some point we have to take what we were given and no matter our current standing, focus on sharpening our skills through practice and continuous learning. It boils down to individual responsibility for our current skill set and progression as a software craftsman. JP’s course does a terrific job of waking you up to that realization and inspiring you to be a better professional at your craft.</p>    <p>I have a few takeaways from the course that I’ll publicly spell out now. First, I (and hopefully our whole team) need to better understand design patterns and have them become integral to our code discussions. JP was all about efficiency in keystrokes and related dev tasks, and it seems natural that our language and code discussions could benefit from more efficient communication using design pattern terminology to convey a lot about a specific design concept in only a few words. Second, I hope that I (and our team again) can really put our tests to work for us, helping us recognize the problem to be solved or the behavior that needs to be captured, and then guiding us toward a simple solution. The third takeaway is related to that last part, and that is to have simple solutions that are distributed across simple object implementations (focusing on behaviors) that adhere to SOLID principles. It appears the key is to not focus on implementation specifics until the very last responsible moment; if done right, the implementations to create should be so clear cut and trivial, almost spelled right out in the tests themselves. It’s hard to put into words, but it seems crucial to focus first on the collaborators needed while designing code at the higher levels, finding ways to offload as much responsibility as possible (at least that’s what it felt like) onto dependencies that have yet to be designed and implemented. Designing Top-Down in this way gave such simple and elegant solutions that were totally extensible and adhered to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open/closed_principle" target="_blank">Open/Closed Principle</a> better than any other code I have ever seen before. Perhaps as I blog more about this, I’ll be able to better put this style of coding into words (especially as I try to better understand it myself; it all seems so magical still!).</p>    <p>Overall, a great course that I highly recommend to all. JP has mentioned doing a similar course in Ruby, which I personally find especially interesting, given the same design/coding techniques would seem to run against a lot less friction compared to the heavy reliance on interfaces and mocking that C# require.</p>    <p>Stay tuned as I try to put some of this stuff into practice!</p> </span>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LINQ Query Syntax and Type Argument Inference]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/12/03/linq-query-syntax-and-type-argument-inference/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-03T15:29:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/12/03/linq-query-syntax-and-type-argument-inference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>In LINQ, you can query in-memory data collections using <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb397947.aspx">Method Syntax (the <font face="Courier New">IEnumerable</font> extension methods) or Query Syntax (the SQL-like, declarative syntactic sugar on top of the underlying method calls)</a>.&#160; I was using the query syntax to join a few in-memory collections and then project (like a SQL <font face="Courier New">SELECT</font>) the denormalized data into a new object that only contained a few pieces of information from each of the separate data collections.&#160; The code could look similar to this (we'll go with a shopping example in honor of the upcoming holiday season):</p>  <pre class="brush: csharp">var shoppingLists =
    from person in people
    join wishlist in wishlists on person.Id equals wishlist.personId
    join store in stores on store.Id equals wishlist.storeId
    select new
    {
        PersonName = person.Name,
        StoreName = store.Name,
        NumItems = wishlist.Items.Count
    };</pre>

<p>However, I ran into the following intellisense red squiggly error in the Visual Studio C# code editor on the second <font face="Courier New">join</font> statement:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><font face="Courier New">The type arguments for method 'IEnumerable&lt;TResult&gt; System.Linq.Enumerable.Join&lt;TOuter,TInner,TKey,TResult&gt;(this IEnumerable&lt;TOuter&gt;, IEnumerable&lt;TInner&gt;, Func&lt;TOuter,TKey&gt;, Func&lt;TInner,TKey&gt;, Func&lt;TOuter,TInner,TResult&gt;)' cannot be inferred from the query.</font></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The error might also end with a statement that says &quot;<font face="Courier New">Try specifiying the type arguments explicitly</font>.&quot;</p>
<span class="fullpost">
  <h3>Let’s Take a Closer Look…</h3>

  <p>The underlying problem is best understood by examining the method signature of the <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb534675.aspx">LINQ <font face="Courier New">Join</font> extension method</a> and how the LINQ query syntax for the keyword <font face="Courier New">join</font> maps to that method call in the compiler.&#160; The type signature for the extension method is as follows:</p>

  <pre class="brush: csharp">public static IEnumerable&lt;TResult&gt; Join&lt;TOuter,TInner,TKey,TResult&gt;(
    this IEnumerable&lt;TOuter&gt; outer,
    IEnumerable&lt;TInner&gt; inner,
    Func&lt;TOuter,TKey&gt; outerKeySelector,
    Func&lt;TInner,TKey&gt; innerKeySelector,
    Func&lt;TOuter,TInner,TResult&gt; resultSelector)</pre>

  <p>Consistent with all <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb383977.aspx">extension methods</a>, it is <font face="Courier New">public static</font> and has a <font face="Courier New">this</font> keyword in front of the first method parameter, allowing you to call the <font face="Courier New">Join</font> method as if it had been declared in the original definition of the <font face="Courier New">IEnumerable&lt;&gt;</font> class or one of its inheriting children classes.</p>

  <p>The first two parameters are the two data collections being joined, and in the case of my LINQ query above, they would be the joined collection of <font face="Courier New">people</font> &amp; <font face="Courier New">wishlists</font> and then the <font face="Courier New">stores</font> collection, respectively.</p>

  <p>The next two method parameters take delegates or lambda expressions that select the key value from each collection participating in the join, <font face="Courier New">outer</font> collection key selector first and then the <font face="Courier New">inner</font> key selector second.&#160; The key values of each item in each collection will compared to each other for equality.&#160; It will use the normal definition of the <font face="Courier New">Equals</font> method for your object type (or if you specified a custom one in your class definition), or there is another <font face="Courier New">Join</font> extension method signature that takes in another method parameter that an object that conforms to the <font face="Courier New"><a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms132151.aspx">IEqualityComparer&lt;TKey&gt; <font face="Arial">interface</font></a></font>.&#160; The key selectors from our LINQ query sample would be the two member access expressions in the &quot;<font face="Courier New">on store.Id equals wishlist.storeId</font><font face="Arial">&quot; statement.</font></p>

  <p>The last parameter is a delegate or lambda expression that takes in a item from each participating data collection and projects the items into a new form (like the <font face="Courier New">Select</font> LINQ query method and its SQL equivalent).&#160; The two items being passed into the <font face="Courier New">Func</font> have passed the equality comparison of each item’s key value, exactly the same as how rows from two tables match up in an <font face="Courier New">inner join</font> statement in SQL.</p>

  <p>As for the <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/0zk36dx2.aspx">generic type parameters</a> in this extension method definition, <font face="Courier New">TOuter</font> and <font face="Courier New">TInner</font> are the types from the two collections participating in the join.&#160; <font face="Courier New">TKey</font> is the type returned by the key selectors; notice that in order to compare the equality of each key selected, they need to be of the same type.&#160; In our example, <font face="Courier New">TKey</font> is likely <font face="Courier New">int</font> or <font face="Courier New">long</font> (or maybe <font face="Courier New">Guid</font>) since we’re dealing with <font face="Courier New">Id</font> properties of all of our objects.&#160; <font face="Courier New">TResult</font> is the type returned by the projection <font face="Courier New">Func&lt;TOuter,TInner,TResult&gt; resultSelector</font>; in our case, we returned an <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb397696.aspx">anonymous type</a> consisting of three properties (<font face="Courier New">PersonName</font>, <font face="Courier New">StoreName</font>, and <font face="Courier New">NumItems</font>).</p>

  <h3>Ok, So Where Did I Screw Up Then?</h3>

  <p>To answer this, let’s take a look one more time at my LINQ query syntax, how it would map to LINQ method syntax, and the <font face="Courier New">Join</font> method signature again all side-by-side:</p>

  <pre class="brush: csharp; highlight: [4,19,20]">var shoppingLists =
    from person in people
    join wishlist in wishlists on person.Id equals wishlist.personId
    join store in stores on store.Id equals wishlist.storeId
    select new
    {
        PersonName = person.Name,
        StoreName = store.Name,
        NumItems = wishlist.Items.Count
    };

// Equivalent LINQ method syntax
var shoppingLists2 = people
    .Join(wishlists,
        person =&gt; person.Id,
        wishlist =&gt; wishlist.personId,
        (person, wishlist) =&gt; new { person, wishlist })
    .Join(stores,
        store =&gt; store.Id,
        something =&gt; something.wishlist.storeId,
        (obj, store) =&gt; new
        {
            PersonName = obj.person.Name,
            StoreName = store.Name,
            NumItems = obj.wishlist.Items.Count
        });

public static IEnumerable&lt;TResult&gt; Join&lt;TOuter,TInner,TKey,TResult&gt;(
    this IEnumerable&lt;TOuter&gt; outer,
    IEnumerable&lt;TInner&gt; inner,
    Func&lt;TOuter,TKey&gt; outerKeySelector,
    Func&lt;TInner,TKey&gt; innerKeySelector,
    Func&lt;TOuter,TInner,TResult&gt; resultSelector)</pre>

  <p>The issue is lines 19 and 20 above; they need to be switched.&#160; The compiler can’t properly infer the generic type parameters because we have our key selectors out of order in the argument list when invoking the <font face="Courier New">Join</font> method.&#160; If you wanted to be explicit about your generic type parameters assignments, then <font face="Courier New">Join&lt;TOuter, TInner, TKey, TResult&gt;</font> would be <font face="Courier New">Join&lt;Temp1, Store, int, Temp2&gt;</font>, where <font face="Courier New">Temp1</font> and <font face="Courier New">Temp2</font> represent the magical type definitions that the compiler creates underneath the covers when you use anonymous types in your C# code.&#160; Notice the <font face="Courier New">outerKeySelector</font> needs to come before the <font face="Courier New">innerKeySelector</font>.&#160; It appears the &quot;<font face="Courier New">on store.Id equals wishlist.storeId</font><font face="Arial">&quot; syntax is not a </font><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commutativity">commutative operation</a>.</p>

  <p>One last thing, I just realized that the error(s) given in Visual Studio when you actually compile the code are different than the intellisense red squiggly error message.&#160; It appears an actual build of the code is able to be a little more omniscient than the quick compile that intellisense does as you type.&#160; The error (and intelligent suggestion) the compiler offers says something like this:</p>

  <blockquote>
    <p><font face="Courier New">The name 'store' is not in scope on the left side of 'equals'.&#160; Consider swapping the expressions on either side of 'equals'.</font></p>
  </blockquote>

  <h3>Additional Info</h3>

  <p>While reading the <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb534675.aspx">MSDN article on the LINQ <font face="Courier New">Join</font> method</a>, I thought the &quot;<font face="Courier New">Remarks</font><font face="Arial">&quot;</font> section has some really great stuff about deferred execution, default equality comparison, differences from <font face="Courier New">SelectMany</font>, sort order perseverance, and so on:</p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>This method is implemented by using deferred execution. The immediate return value is an object that stores all the information that is required to perform the action. The query represented by this method is not executed until the object is enumerated either by calling its <strong>GetEnumerator</strong> method directly or by using foreach in Visual C# or For Each in Visual Basic.</p>

    <p>The default equality comparer, <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms224763.aspx">Default</a>, is used to hash and compare keys.</p>

    <p>A join refers to the operation of correlating the elements of two sources of information based on a common key. <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.linq.enumerable.join.aspx">Join</a> brings the two information sources and the keys by which they are matched together in one method call. This differs from the use of <strong>SelectMany</strong>, which requires more than one method call to perform the same operation.</p>

    <p><a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.linq.enumerable.join.aspx">Join</a> preserves the order of the elements of outer, and for each of these elements, the order of the matching elements of inner.</p>

    <p>In query expression syntax, a join (Visual C#) or Join (Visual Basic) clause translates to an invocation of <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.linq.enumerable.join.aspx">Join</a>.</p>

    <p>In relational database terms, the <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.linq.enumerable.join.aspx">Join</a> method implements an inner equijoin. 'Inner' means that only elements that have a match in the other sequence are included in the results. An 'equijoin' is a join in which the keys are compared for equality. A left outer join operation has no dedicated standard query operator, but can be performed by using the <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.linq.enumerable.groupjoin.aspx">GroupJoin</a> method. See <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb397908.aspx">Join Operations</a>.</p>
  </blockquote>

  <p>Thanks, I hope this proves helpful to someone, as it was certainly eye-opening to me.</p>
</span></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maybe Monad Extensions]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/09/30/maybe-monad-extensions/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-30T17:35:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkmurray.com/blog/2010/09/30/maybe-monad-extensions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I learned a lot from <a href="http://murrayon.net/2010/09/maybe-from-murray-monads.html" target="_blank">my last foray into implementing my own Maybe Monad</a>.&#160; Apparently, it got noticed by and was actually useful to <a href="http://www.lostechies.com/members/derick.bailey/default.aspx" target="_blank">Derick Bailey</a>, as it was one of the resources he used in <a href="http://www.lostechies.com/blogs/derickbailey/archive/2010/09/29/monads-in-c-which-part-is-the-monad.aspx" target="_blank">his own personal exploration into Monads</a>.&#160; Of course, Derick did the topic a bit more justice, as he has a propensity to do.</p>  <p>Nonetheless, I have done as I said I would and reworked my Murray Monads into a cleaner, more concise implementation using extension methods, much like the implementation I introduced from Dmitri Nesteruk in the last post.&#160; So without further ado, I’d like to introduce you to the MaybeMonadExtensions.</p> <span class="fullpost">   <h4>Monads 2.0 - <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ll7rWiY5obI&amp;t=1m19s" target="_blank">“These Go To Eleven”</a></h4>    <p>If you want to get an introduction to what Monads are and how I got to where I am today with this little library, then you really should check out <a href="http://murrayon.net/2010/09/maybe-from-murray-monads.html" target="_blank">the previous post on this topic</a>.&#160; I will however give a few brief code samples to show you what it can do to tidy up all those null checks using the Maybe Monad.</p>    <p>Here is code we tend to write all the time:</p>    <pre class="brush: csharp">string postCode;
if (person != null)
{
  if (HasMedicalRecord(person) &amp;&amp; person.Address != null)
  {
    CheckAddress(person.Address);
    if (person.Address.PostCode != null)
      postCode = person.Address.PostCode.ToString();
    else
      postCode = &quot;UNKNOWN&quot;;
  }
}</pre>

  <p>It can look like this with some Maybe Monad love:</p>

  <pre class="brush: csharp">string postalCode = person.If(HasMedicalRecord)
  .Access(p =&gt; p.Address)
  .Apply(CheckAddress)
  .Access(a =&gt; a.PostCode)
  .Convert(pc =&gt; pc.ToString(), &quot;UNKNOWN&quot;);</pre>

  <p>I know!&#160; Groovy, huh?!</p>

  <p>The source can be found here:&#160; <a href="http://bitbucket.org/murrayondotnet/maybemonadextensions/">http://bitbucket.org/murrayondotnet/maybemonadextensions/</a></p>

  <p>Let me know if you put this to good use!</p>
</span>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Omer Mor</div>
<div class='content'>
I see your point.<br />However, even Rx is sharing many LINQ operators with its IObservable &amp; IQbservable monads.<br />So we already have 4 different monads (IEnumerable, IQueryable, IObservable, IQbservable) using those operators. I don&#39;t think any more would hurt :-)</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mike Murray</div>
<div class='content'>
Great question. I suppose I could have used those names and it would likely be a familiar vernacular for .NET developers. I guess my only hesitation would be that I wouldn&#39;t necessarily want to confuse others who read the code into thinking that they are LINQ extension methods. My first thought when I saw your code was that somehow person was an IQueryable or IEnumerable, just because of those familiar method names.<br /><br />Great point though, and it does make me second guess my chosen names a bit. I did like Derick&#39;s method names too (especially just plain old &quot;Get&quot;). Thanks for posting!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Omer Mor</div>
<div class='content'>
Nice.<br /><br />Why didn&#39;t you choose the Linq terminology here?<br />I&#39;d write your example as this (Linq + Rx&#39;s Do operator):<br /><br /><br />string postalCode = person.Where(HasMedicalRecord)<br />  .Select(p =&gt; p.Address)<br />  .Do(CheckAddress)<br />  .Select(a =&gt; a.PostCode)<br />  .Select(pc =&gt; pc.ToString(), &quot;UNKNOWN&quot;);</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
